<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest and peaceable inquiry into the design and nature of some of those historical mistakes that are found in Dr. Stillingfleet's preface to his Unreasonableness of separation wherein the innocency of Protestant dissenters is cleared up and vindicated from the indecent censures of the doctor / by N. B.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8947</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11806495</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11806495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49455</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45143)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49455)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 538:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest and peaceable inquiry into the design and nature of some of those historical mistakes that are found in Dr. Stillingfleet's preface to his Unreasonableness of separation wherein the innocency of Protestant dissenters is cleared up and vindicated from the indecent censures of the doctor / by N. B.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
                  <author>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Humfrey and Stephen Lobb. Cf. Halkett and Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Unreasonableness of separation.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49455:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49455:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MODEST and PEACEABLE INQUIRY INTO THE DESIGN and NATURE OF Some of thoſe Hiſtorical Miſtakes That are found in Dr. Stillingfleet's PREFACE TO HIS <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of SEPARATION.</hi> WHEREIN The Innocency of Proteſtant Diſſenters is cleared up and Vindicated from the indecent Cenſures of the Doctor.</p>
            <p>By <hi>N. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Out of thine own mouth will: judg thee.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 19.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49455:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49455:2"/>
            <head>To the REVEREND Dr. Stillingfleet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TIS well known unto you, that the <hi>Ruin</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and of the Churches of Chriſt in it, hath been ever ſince the <hi>Firſt Reformation,</hi> aimed at by the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> whoſe rage hath not only appeared in the many little Plots that have been from time to time diſcover'd; but even in their <hi>Rebellions</hi> and <hi>Inſurrections</hi> in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s days. The <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s. The <hi>Gun-Powder</hi> Treaſon in King <hi>James,</hi> &amp;c. and this l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te <hi>Helliſh Conſpiracy,</hi> which was deſign'd for the utter Extirpation of the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Univerſal deſtruction of all the Profeſſors thereof, whether <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> or <hi>Diſſenter.</hi> For which reaſon, this is no time to add fewel to the Fire of Proteſtant Diſſentions. Nor is it meet to inſiſt on any matter of <hi>Indifference</hi> ſo far as thereby to hinder a <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>laſting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> among <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> If the Diſſenters can without offence to God, and wrong to their <hi>own Conſciences</hi> comply with the <hi>Terms</hi> impos'd by you for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> their non-compliance is a ſin, that in its tendencies advances Popery: But if the Diſſenter cannot conſcientiouſly conform to your <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> as they really cannot, and you <hi>can</hi> without <hi>ſin</hi> make ſuch eaſie <hi>Overtures</hi> for Peace, as may be <hi>grateful</hi> to Diſſenters, your refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in this caſe to comply, doth ſufficiently evince <hi>You</hi> to be the <hi>Divider,</hi> and <hi>Promoter</hi> of the <hi>Papacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Diſſenters being ſincerely deſirous to do the utmoſt they can without ſin for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> you greatly injure them in repreſenting them as Enemies thereunto. 'Tis true, you cry up <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> but you will not part with what you judg but a trifle, for it. You cry down Diſſenters as enemies to Peace and Concord, as Schiſmaticks, Factions
<pb facs="tcp:49455:3"/>and Seditious, as Friends to <hi>Popery,</hi> expoſing them to the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and rage of your <hi>Conſidents,</hi> as if their <hi>Conſciences</hi> were but <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,</hi> their <hi>ſenſe of Scripture</hi> but <hi>fancy,</hi> their <hi>Sincerity</hi> in embracing the Proteſtant Religion but <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> their <hi>Zeal</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Reformation</hi> but a <hi>blaſting</hi> it, and their <hi>Oppoſition</hi> unto <hi>Popery</hi> a <hi>promoting</hi> it. But is this <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>equal?</hi> Doth <hi>ſuch</hi> a Procedure become the Learning, the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and Religion of Dr. <hi>Stilling ſleet?</hi> Can you in your more cool de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberations reflect on all this with uninterrupted peace? What, without any rebukes or checks of Conſcience?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> Can you conſider, how <hi>untrue,</hi> as well as how <hi>ſevere</hi> the charge is with which you load your Diſſenting Brethren? or can you think on the many <hi>miſtakes</hi> on which you ground your charge, and yet believe that all this may return to your comfortable account another day? Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks there is a ſmart rebuke attending the method of your Procedure, namely, that in your reproaching the Diſſenters as Promoters of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> deſigns, you ſhould <hi>unawares</hi> make a diſcovery of your ſelf as <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>one;</hi> for certainly you have in your <hi>Preface,</hi> yea and in your <hi>Book,</hi> ſaid enough for the advancing the <hi>Papiſls</hi> Deſigns, juſt as <hi>F. Thomas Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Caraſa,</hi> who in his delineating the Excellencies of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth did moſt exactly (though <hi>unawares</hi>) give the Pourtraiture of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> for Dedicating ſome <hi>Theſes</hi> unto this Pope, he did it thus, <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LO V. VICE DEO,</hi> &amp;c. ſome <hi>Novelles</hi> of which, being ſent unto <hi>Venice</hi> and elſewhere, it was ſoon noiſed about the <hi>City,</hi> that 'twas the <hi>Picture</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> for that the Inſcription <hi>pa<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Lo V. VICe Deo,</hi> contain'd in the Numerical Letters the number of the Beaſt in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> 666. Of which my Author Mr. <hi>Bedell</hi> in his Anſwer unto Mr. <hi>Wadſworth</hi>'s Letter, ſaith, Whom could they blame but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by their approving of ſuch an <hi>Inſcription</hi> as unawares by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God ſhould ſo plainly <hi>characterize</hi> Antichriſt? In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it may be ſaid of you, ſeeing in the management of your ſmart charge againſt Diſſenters, you have <hi>unawares</hi> (if not deſignedly) clos'd with ſuch <hi>Principles,</hi> and <hi>magnified</hi> ſuch <hi>Arguments</hi> as prove advantageous to none but the <hi>Papal Intereſt,</hi> whom can you blame but your ſelf? or how can you obſerve the nature of this unwary ſlip, without ſome inward chick?</p>
            <p>That you ſhould expoſe your ſelf in ſuch circumſtances without any provocation, doth abundantly ſuprize, and that in ſo many a particular inſtance, beſide what I have mention'd under the third head in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Enquiry, is conſiderable: For,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49455:3"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. You ſay, That 'tis no improbable that the Jeſuits were the firſt ſetters up of <hi>ſpiritual prayer;</hi> you mean of its <hi>publick</hi> exerciſe, or ſpeak not to the purpoſe, ſeeing 'tis <hi>that</hi> the Diſſenters plead for in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates with the Epiſcopal, and 'tis <hi>that</hi> by which they gain ſo much in the eſteem of the people. But <hi>this</hi> the Jeſuits are againſt, they agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with you in that they are only for the exerciſe of <hi>free</hi> Prayer in <hi>private and not in publick,</hi> juſt as the famous Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> who ſpeaking of <hi>Private Prayer,</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hooker.</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Poii<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib. <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>223, 225.</hi> Ed. ult.</note> 
                  <q>That '<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s a duty perform'd by us as men, and that we are at our <hi>own choice,</hi> both for <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> and <hi>from,</hi> according to the exigence of our own occaſions in <hi>private.</hi> — But publick Prayer muſt be according to ſome preſcribed form.</q> Which exactly agreeth with that of <hi>Bellarmine, Azorius,</hi> and <hi>Filliucius;</hi> all <hi>Jeſuits.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. You charge your <hi>Brethren</hi> as if they had oppos'd an <hi>Abſolute,</hi> or an <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Antiquity, becauſe they believe not your <hi>Hierarchy</hi> to be ſuch; but you <hi>unawares</hi> have fallen in with <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in exalting ſuch an <hi>Antiquity</hi> he pleads for, ſupporting it with ſuch arguments as are ſetcht out of the Jeſuits Storehouſe, to the great diſſatisfaction of the old <hi>Epiſcopal Proteſtants,</hi> as I have ſhewn out of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. You inſiſt much on the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> as if it had been the Bulwark of the Proteſtant Religion, but <hi>unawares</hi> have ſo far gratified the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> as to be freed from their black Character of <hi>Hereſie;</hi> for 'tis obſerv'd by ſome <hi>Epiſcopal Divines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Deſper. <hi>Calvin.</hi> cauſ. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Cudſemius</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> ſaith, <q>That the <hi>Calvinian</hi> Sect in <hi>England,</hi> may either endure long, or be ſuddenly chang'd in a trice, in regard of the <hi>Catholick Order there,</hi> in a perpetual line of their Biſhops, and the lawful ſucceſſion of Paſtors received from the <hi>Church;</hi> for the <hi>Honour</hi> of which we uſe to call the <hi>Engliſh Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts</hi> [<hi>i.e.</hi> the Epiſcopal] by a milder term, not <hi>Hereticks,</hi> but <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.</hi>
                  </q>
               </item>
               <item>4. You repreſent the Diſſenters as ſubſervient to the Papal intereſt, becauſe they are not for <hi>uninſtituted ceremonies,</hi> yea you ſuggeſt as if a Ceremony had been in greater eſtimation with you than the peace of truly tender Conſciences; whereby you do <hi>unawares</hi> furniſh the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> with a ſtrong argument for the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of a Ceremony; for ſaith <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49455:4"/>Ceremonies are a momentous parts of worſhip, becauſe there have been great Deſſentions in the Church about Ceremonies, which ought not to be about leſſer matters.</item>
               <item>5. You ſay the Diſſenters by their Nonconformity have blaſted the Honour of the firſt Reformation; But as this is untrue, even ſo you have by inſiſting on it <hi>unawares</hi> advantaged the <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> do judg honourably of the firſt Reformation, may appear from the account we give of it thus:</p>
            <p>As it muſt be acknowledged, that there were in theſe Lands many concern'd for a <hi>Reformation</hi> about <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and ſome other things before <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighths, even ſo in his time a <hi>Reformation</hi> of the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> began, which was carried on by <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth that Pious Prince, the wonder of his age; in whoſe time, although the Reformation went on <hi>gloriouſly,</hi> yet very <hi>ſlowly,</hi> becauſe of the many <hi>Hindrances</hi> were in its way. For,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Many of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Clergy being zealous for their old <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions,</hi> yea even the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> did much miſchief in impeding the Reformation.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>generality</hi> of the people <hi>devoted</hi> to the <hi>Traditions</hi> of their <hi>forefathers,</hi> would rather run the hazard of the loſs of their lives, than of one <hi>ceremony.</hi> As appears,
<list>
                     <item>1. By the many <hi>Inſurrections</hi> and <hi>Rebellions</hi> in ſeveral Counties, eſpecially in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. From the great <hi>Neglect</hi> ſhewn concerning his Majeſties <hi>Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>Proclamations, Acts of Parliament,</hi> and <hi>divers Letters</hi> ſent from the Council unto the ſeveral Juſtices of every County for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting <hi>Reformation.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The <hi>unhappy Diviſions</hi> between the <hi>Kings <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> the Duke of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> the then <hi>Protector,</hi> and other <hi>Lords of the Council.</hi> To which add,</item>
                     <item>4. The <hi>Kings</hi> being <hi>under age,</hi> (which was abus'd by the <hi>Papiſt</hi>) and alſo the <hi>ſhortneſs</hi> of his Reign. All which duly weighed, it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt even by the greateſt enemies to our Religion, that 'twas a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:49455:4"/>Providence that ſo great a Progreſs was made in ſo ſhort a time. Sur<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 'twas <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> and the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> imploy'd in ſo <hi>excellent</hi> a work deſerve our greateſt <hi>Praiſes,</hi> in that they acted ſo <hi>wiſely</hi> in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the work of Reformation, which was carried on thus <hi>gradually.</hi> For,
<list>
                           <item>1. Though <hi>Tho. Dobb</hi> was caſt into the <hi>Breadſtreet Counter,</hi> where he died for ſpeaking againſt the <hi>Idolatry of the Maſs,</hi> beſide one <hi>John Hume,</hi> we find no other Proſecution of <hi>Poenal Laws</hi> againſt <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>But, 2. <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> were ſent out to endeavour a <hi>preſent Reformation</hi> as to ſome Particulars.</item>
                           <item>3. A <hi>Parliament</hi> call'd for the Repealing ſome Poenal Statutes. <hi>Free liberty</hi> given <hi>publickly</hi> to profeſs the Goſpel. Many zealous Freachers before Baniſhed, <hi>Licenſed</hi> to return and <hi>Preach.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. Certain of the moſt <hi>Grave,</hi> and beſt <hi>Learned Biſhops</hi> by his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Order aſſemble at <hi>Windſor.</hi> Caſtle, who did draw up a <hi>form of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments,</hi> which was ſent abroad into the ſeveral <hi>Dioceſſes,</hi> about which there ariſing great <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Schiſms</hi> among the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Clergy;</item>
                           <item>5. His <hi>Majeſty</hi> engageth the Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to compoſe that Book, Entituled, <hi>A Book of Common-Prayer, &amp;c.</hi> which was approved of, and eſtabliſhed by the Parliament.</item>
                           <item>Yet, 6. Though this Service-Book was ſo admirably well ſuited to the <hi>capacity</hi> of the Vulgar, who were ſo zealous for their old Superſtitions, the People be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ignorant,</hi> made an <hi>Inſurrection</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> and <hi>Cornwall,</hi> to whom his <hi>Majesty</hi> in a Letter expreſſeth himſelf thus: <q>As for the Service in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, it hath manifeſt reaſons for it. And yet perchance it ſeemeth to you a <hi>New Service,</hi> and indeed is none other but the old, the ſelf-ſame <hi>words</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> which were in <hi>Latin,</hi> &amp;c. <bibl>
                                    <hi>Act. Mon.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                              </q> 
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Thus the firſt Reformers, as <hi>indeed,</hi> even ſo in the <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> did their utmoſt in King <hi>Edwards</hi> days, and in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> did diſcover a zeal of doing more, might they furvive that Perſecution: In purſuance of which <hi>Reſolutions,</hi> ſeveral who either ſuffer'd under Q. <hi>Mary</hi> at home, or were in exile abroad, in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, did ſeriouſly attempt a further. Reformation, for their doing which, they have been branded as Schiſmaticks, Dividers, and promoters of Popiſh deſigns by ſuch as will not ſo far <hi>honour</hi> the beginnings of King <hi>Edwards</hi> Reformation by endeavours to promote it. All this you know, and therefore in obliging all to reſt ſatisfied with a Reformation wreſted out of Popiſh hands in a time of the greateſt difficulties, which could <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot <hi>then</hi> be more than what Popiſh <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Bonner</hi> and <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuer conform'd unto,</hi> you do greatly advantage the Papal intereſt by drawing us <hi>gradatim</hi> from our greater Reformation, unto what was carried on in King <hi>Edwards</hi> days, and it may be for the <hi>ſame</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:49455:5"/>you will perſwade us to that of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, which is but one ſtep further back, and ſo on.</p>
            <p>But whether you have not offended God in this <hi>indecent procedure,</hi> I leave to your own more ſerious conſiderations, humbly beſeeching you to meditate on thoſe following hints given us by a Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (Mr. <hi>Down,</hi>) who in his Preſervative againſt the contempt of the Miniſtry, expreſſeth himſelf thus, <q>It is a fearful ſpeech of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Quis unquam Clericum lapſum pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentem vidit?</hi> Whoever ſaw a Miniſter recover himſelf after a fall by repentance? And indeed it is but ſeldom ſeen; for the fins that are ſingle in others, being double in him, and an idle word in anothers mouth being as it were Blaſphemy in his; God puniſheth him more rigorouſly than he doth others.—The ſtrongeſt wine turneth into the ſharpeſt vinegar, and the Nobleſt Angels ſinning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the vileſt Devils.</q> In like manner it is with us.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>You cannot but be ſenſible of the dangers we are in, of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Love, Peace and Concord among our ſelves, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the evil tendencies of the method you have taken, in the untrue Accuſations you have laid in againſt the innocent Diſſenters, the <hi>miſtakes</hi> you are guilty of in the proſecuting that your deſign, and the unwary ſlips that prove advantageous to our common enemy the Papiſts, and in fine of the ſervice this inconſiderable tract may be of, in ſetting you right; I ſay you being ſenſible of all this, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding requeſt ſhall be, that you will put the moſt candid comment on this eſſay, and joyn with me in this Letany.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>From all
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Seditions.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Miſchievous Impoſitions, ſinful Separations,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Cenſurers,</hi> and <hi>Falſe Accuſers;</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list> Good Lord deliver us. I am <hi>Your Faithful Servant</hi> N. B.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAGE 32. line 22. read <hi>ſuch.</hi> Page 33. line 8. read <hi>ſome one.</hi> Page 34. line 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> dele <hi>by.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49455:5"/>
            <head>A Modeſt, and Peaceable <hi>Inquiry</hi> into the Deſign and Nature of Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet's</hi> HISTORICAL MISTAKES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SUch are the Calamities of the Reformed Churches both at home and abroad, ſo great and ſo many, that it high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns all true Proteſtants to do their utmoſt for the Defence of them. Our Enemies are men of Bloody De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, Active Spirits, Undaunted, notwithſtanding the moſt ſurprizing Diſappointments, and unwearied in a brisk Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Helliſh Plots, turning every Stone if poſſible to Ruin us Eternally, and nothing but a ſincere Reformation, and a <hi>firm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> among our ſelves can contribute in any meaſure (unleſs God act by an uncommon Prerogative) towards our ſafety. Our own Diviſions, Heats, Animoſities and Quarrels, are but as the Enemies ſword ſheathed in our own Bowels; our mutual Jealouſies, undue ſuſpitions and Revilings of each other, tend but to the ſtrengthning the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Intereſt and the haſtening our own Rume, unto which, if ever we periſh by the hands of the <hi>Roman</hi> Faction, we muſt aſſign the great Cauſe of our Miſeries; But 'tis a ſpecial Providence of an Infinitely wiſe and Gracious God, that 'tis in the heart of our <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite</hi> and <hi>ſave us;</hi> the which Noble Deſign may be compaſs'd, unleſs the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> and <hi>Diſſenting</hi> Clergy by their own <hi>indiſcretions</hi> impede and hinder it.</p>
            <p>For this Reaſon, 'tis become moſt unſeaſonable to beat the Drum, or ſound the Trumpet for a Proteſtant Civil-wordy-War; To contend at this time about Triſles, or to mind the Tithing, Mint, Cummin, or Anniſe, when the weighty matters of the Proteſtant Religion are in Danger: To be over-ſevere in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Impoſitions</hi> on the one ſide, or over-ſcrupulous in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing <hi>juſt compliances</hi> on the other, is to contend about the <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49455:6"/>even when the <hi>Subſtance</hi> is ready to be violently taken from us by the mighty Torrent of Popiſh Treachery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If our Learned Worthies, whether of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Diſſenters, <hi>will</hi> diſpute the Matters in difference, why may it not be done with more Calmneſs and Serenity of Mind? what need of Perſonal Reflections, Angry or ſcolding Repartees? what need of a <hi>Metabaſis,</hi> a running from the Subject-Matter, to wit, from the Argument to the Diſputant? Doth it in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner inlighten the Mind, or convince the Gainſayer, what are the advantages of ſuch a procedure? Methinks it ought to be matter of <hi>Lamentation,</hi> rather th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Triumph,</hi> to ſee the Church in its preſent bleeding poſture, and with all our Champions, whoſe ſtrength ſhould be turn'd againſt the common Enemy, to be at Daggers point among themſelves.</p>
            <p>That ſuch a Conteſt as this, between the Reverend Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet,</hi> and his <hi>learned Adverſaries</hi> ſhould happen at this Juncture, cannot but ſill the hearts of all ſober Proteſtants of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſwaſion with ſad Thoughts; but that it ſhould be managed with ſo much <hi>ſmartneſs,</hi> muſt much more afflict us. 'Tis true, Dr. <hi>O.</hi> after the occaſion was firſt given, return'd his Anſwer to Dr. <hi>S's.</hi> Sermon not only learnedly, and judiciouſly, but, with that <hi>even Temper,</hi> became a Proteſtant Divine; and I wiſh that ſuch others as engag'd in the ſame quarrel had ſo manag'd it, as to deſerve the ſame Character. 'Tis admirably expreſs'd by <hi>Franc. a Sanct a Clara,</hi> in the Preface of his Tract de Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. &amp;c. <hi>Mali habentibus opus eſt medico,</hi> non ſevero, <hi>ſed</hi> benigno, <hi>non dicteriis arictando,</hi> ſed <hi>dictis placidis modo ſolidis, aggrediendo.</hi> Solid Arguments cloath'd with the moſt pleaſing words are more convincing, than thoſe that are offer'd either two <hi>ſmartly,</hi> or too <hi>facetiouſly.</hi> But whilſt we carry about us the bodies of Sin, we can more eaſily declaim againſt humane infirmities, than amend them; And when we have done our utmoſt, there muſt be a Regard to the humour of a Diſputant, yea, and a mutual forbearance, beſide that reſpect, which muſt be had to our <hi>Readers,</hi> who either will not conſider what hath not in it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>grateful</hi> with the Argument, or who think no Argument <hi>ſtrong,</hi> but what is ſatyrically expreſſed.</p>
            <p>But the Ball is up, and ſmart blows have paſſed, and every Party inflam'd. The Reverend <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi> thinks himſelf unjuſtly injur'd by his Oppoſers; and that he may be even with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49455:6"/>them, has ſufficiently reflected on all Proteſtant Diſſenters, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the Error for which he rebukes ſome others. The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters in like manner judge themſelves as highly wronged by the Doctor. The Honour of the Dr. is impeached, the peace of the Diſſenter broke, and their hoped for Liberties in hazard, which being ſo, 'tis become a difficulty to faſten on a juſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for the accommadating this pernicious controverſie: The fury of the ſire is ſuch, that who ever will attempt the quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, is in danger of being conſumed by the Flames thereof; for either the one or the other will be diſpleaſed; for though ſomething muſt be ſaid to clear the innocent: Yet what Perſon ſoever undertakes it, muſt either ſpeak the Truth and offend the Doctor or conceale it, and grieve the Innocent to the wounding his own Conſcience. But notwithſtanding theſe <hi>Intricacies,</hi> I will preſume to make this modeſt <hi>Eſſay</hi> in a ſober Addreſs unto the Dr. beſeeching him candidly to interpret my Zeal for Truth, Faithfulneſs to the Proteſtant Religion, and Love to the peace of the Church, and his and my own Conſcience. Not that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to engage ſo far in the Skirmiſh, as to concerne my ſelfe about what ſo many a Learned and Judicious Perſon as the Drs. Adverſaries, are more immediately obliged to conſider: I will not invade either of their Provinces, and yet I will make ſome inſpection into the Nature of that charge, with which he ſeems to endeavour the blaſting the untainted Reputation of truly Loyal and ſincere (though diſſenting) Proteſtants. In purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of which end.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I will propoſe the deſign of the Drs. <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> being chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably; diſpoſed to diſtinguiſh between the <hi>finis operis, &amp; operantis</hi> for though the end of the <hi>Work it ſelf</hi> cannot but in its tendency prove pernicious to the Proteſtant Religion; yet I hope the Dr. deſigned it not as ſuch.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I will ſhew his <hi>miſtakes</hi> concerning the account he gives of the Diſſenting Brethren, and evince that the Reaſons urg'd to engage the Reader to believe that the Diſſenters, are a People carrying on the Popiſh Deſigns, are of ſuch a Nature as cannot but move a thinking and unbyaſſed Mind to Judge the Author himſelf to be the Perſon who alone under a diſguiſe doth ſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I will acquaint you with the great diſadvantages the Dr. Expoſeth himſelf unto, by the Method he hath taken to reproach <hi>us:</hi> The Principles From which he muſt and doth raiſe the Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49455:7"/>he maketh againſt Diſſenters, being ſuch as are found in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and the moſt noted Champions of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi> And</p>
            <p n="4">4. In fine I will in a way moſt fair and candid evince, how reaſonable it is, that the Dr. (if he will do the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and himſelf but right;) make either a more full, diſtinct, and clear diſcovery of his thoughts, or a <hi>Retractation</hi> of what in this late Diſcourſe he hath ſuggeſted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Deſign of the Hiſtory in the Preface is to miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſſenting Proteſtants by his falſe Accuſations, which are <q>That they do carry on the <hi>Papiſts work for them,</hi> that they hold ſuch <hi>Principles,</hi> as by evident conſequences from them do <hi>overthrow the Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity of the Reformation,</hi> preface. p. 6. and out of <hi>Biſhop Sanderſon</hi> 'tis aſſerted, That the Diſſenting Brethren, though not intentionally and purpoſely, yet <hi>really,</hi> and <hi>eventually</hi> have been the great <hi>Promoters</hi> of the <hi>Roman Inte: reſt</hi> among us. — I do not ſay (adds the Dr.) that ſuch men, (namely the Diſſenters) are ſet on by the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> But I ſay they do their work as effectually in blaſting the Credit of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; as if they were. p. 10 — But if we trace the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of their Separation as far as we can, we may find ſtrong probabilities, that the <hi>Jeſuitical Party</hi> had a very great influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the very firſt beginnings of it — And the Papiſts could not but pleaſe themſelves to ſee that other men did their work ſo effectually for them. p. 16. The Papiſts could not have met with better Proctors (<hi>i. e.</hi> then the Diſſenters) they did the <hi>Pope</hi> very good ſervice, and he would not miſs them for any thing. —</q> The Pope could not have fitter and apter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for his Purpoſe. The Diſſenters were made the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines</hi> of the <hi>Roman Conclave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus tis evident that the great end of the Drs. Hiſtory, if not of the whole Book it ſelf, is to repreſent Diſſenting Proteſtants to be but the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Inſtruments, that is, to be men, not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of any favour from a Proteſtant Prince, for ſurely ſuch are the Jeſuits Engines. But as no ſuggeſtion can be more <hi>untrue,</hi> even ſo nothing could proceed from the Drs. Pen more unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably; what ſhould provoke him to be ſo invective and ſatyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal in this juncture of affairs is not eaſie to determine, or what was his end is as difficult to imagine; whether it was to caſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt on the Wiſdom of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who entertain other
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49455:7"/>ſentiments concerning the Diſſenters; or whether to <hi>gratifie the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faction,</hi> by acting ſo ſutably to the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> meaſures as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> and ſome others, which is to revile the Diſſenters, as the Dr. hath done; to the end the common People may be prepared to believe, that whatever horrid Plots the Papiſts are carrying on, are but <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> The which can no ſooner be believed, but his Maieſties moſt Loyal Subjects are expoſed to the mercileſs cruelty of the <hi>bloody Papiſts,</hi> who will not boggle at falſe <hi>Oaths,</hi> to accuſe them of the worſt of <hi>Treaſons</hi> under the Name of <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> or <hi>Diſſenting Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi> Or whether it be to caſt a <hi>Bone of contention</hi> into the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Houſe;</hi> thereby to prevent the uniting and ſtrengthening the Proteſtant Intereſt, as well as for diverting the Houſe from ſuch other Methods as are moſt neceſſary for the impeding the Future growth of Popery; or whether to raiſe one of the ſevereſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions againſt that Loyal and truly Proteſtant Party; which cannot be weakned or impoveriſhed but to the advancing the Papal deſign; whether any one, or all of theſe particulars have been aimed at by the Dr. the Searcher of Hearts, and his own Conſcience doth beſt know. But whatever was the Authors end, 'tis moſt uncontroulably true, that if theſe ſeveral Miſchiefs do not proceed from the Diſcourſe, it muſt be conſidered as a ſignal Providence, to which alone we are owing for ſuch preventing Grace. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. To Exerciſe the <hi>Charity</hi> of collecting ſuch Arguments as are ſubtly <hi>Inſinuated</hi> for the enſnaring the Credulity of ſome of his Readers; The which I will with the greateſt fairneſs ſet forth in their ſtrength, and then deſcend to a detecting the <hi>Miſtakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To give the Dr. the greater advantage, we'l conſider his Arguments to be as <hi>numerous</hi> as is poſſible, after this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Diſſenters have embrac'd the <hi>Jeſuits Principles</hi> about Spiritual Prayer, and a more pure way of worſhip.</item>
               <item>2. They have blaſted the Reputation and Honour of the firſt Reformation.</item>
               <item>3. They oppoſe Epiſcopacy, and innocent Ceremonies not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their <hi>Antiquity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. They have ſeparated from the Church of England, and have cauſ'd great Diviſions.</item>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49455:8"/>
               <item>5. They accepted of his Majeſties gracious Toleration given them 7 or 8 years ago.</item>
               <item>6. They have ſince the diſcovery of the Plot cloſed with the people in an over fierce oppoſing the papiſts. Ergo the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are the</hi> Jeſuits <hi>Inſtruments deſigning the Deſtruction of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion,</hi> This is the Drs. Concluſion, drawn from theſe ſix weighty conſiderations.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. To inquire into the <hi>ſtrength,</hi> or rather the <hi>miſtakes</hi> of theſe weighty conſiderations.</p>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>1. The firſt Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>'Tis not improbable that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were the firſt ſetters up of <hi>Spiritual Prayer</hi> in England ſaith the Dr. as appears from the ſutableneſs of the Diſſenters pretences about Spiritual Prayer, to the Doctrine, and practice of the Jeſuits, This is evinced from the Jeſuits admiring Spiritual Prayer, as may be ſeen in their writings, preface <hi>p.</hi> 14.15.16.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The whole the Dr. doth ſuggeſt is but a <hi>Probability,</hi> not a <hi>certainty,</hi> but why the Dr. ſhould hint his <hi>probables</hi> in a matter of this moment I leave to his own Conſcience,</p>
               <p n="2">2 'Tis moſt undoubtedly true, whether the Dr. knows ſo much or not, <hi>That Spiritual Prayer</hi> and <hi>free prayer</hi> was <hi>many an hundred years obſerv'd,</hi> and <hi>practiſed</hi> before there were any <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in the World, whence to aſſert Spiritual Prayer to be one of the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its Arcana</hi> is an argument of too much ignorance; for who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that the Chriſtian diſpenſation is the diſpenſation of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8. &amp;c 'tis the <hi>Spirit</hi> that was promiſed as a teaching Spirit on Chriſts departure, <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 15, 26.16.7, 8, 9. which Spirit as it doth convince of Sin, of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and of judgment, even ſo doth it teach and enable the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God to cry <hi>Abba Father;</hi> that is to <hi>pray, Gal.</hi> 4.5, 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. Thus Free Prayer or Spiritual Prayer is clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in Scripture. Unto whom then are we owing for the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of this <hi>Truth,</hi> unto the Word of God contained in Scripture, or unto the Diſciples of <hi>Ignatius Loyola?</hi> what, muſt the Honour of the Diſcovery be aſcribed to the Jeſuits, although thereby the Primitive Chriſtians, and the Ancient Fathers are moſt unjuſtly reproached? Or, becauſe this Goſpel Doctrine ſhines forth ſo Gloriouſly, that ſuch as are envelop'd with the Cloud of Popery, cannot but eſpie ſome of its <hi>Rayes;</hi> muſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49455:8"/>we therefore conclude that it hath its <hi>Riſe</hi> and <hi>Origen</hi> from thence? What do the <hi>Papiſts</hi> know nothing beſides thoſe <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of which they were the firſt Inventors. What think you of the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity, &amp;c.</hi> is that alſo a Jeſuits Fiction?</p>
               <p>Really I am not a little ſurprized at the <hi>Indecent</hi> manner, after which the Dr. treats the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> the third Perſon in the ever bleſſed Trinity, by aſcribing its <hi>work,</hi> Namely, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Prayer unto the Jeſuits, as though ſuch are the works of the Spirit, that they cannot be diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Inventions</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuite;</hi> and that the Dr. ſhould thus expoſe himſelf, the honour of his Learning, or good will to the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in a caſe ſo plain, is aſtoniſhing; who knoweth not, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, is as much, or more ſo, for <hi>Free and Spiritual Prayer,</hi> than the Jeſuits are; The heaping up Authorities for this, would be but to follow the Doctor, in raiſing a ſuſpition of the Churches Orthodoxie; when as Free Prayer in Private, which is the utmoſt the Jeſuits are for, is allowed us by the Church of <hi>England;</hi> yea, and commended to our Practice, with helps vouchſafed us by ſome Worthy Divines of this Church; as ſo many expedients Adapted for the obtaining the Gift of Free Prayer, which is not, as I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly apprehend forbidden any Miniſter in Publick; ſuppoſing he neglects not the preſcribed Formes. But to conſider the Drs. Integrity in the Hiſtory he gives concerning this, by whom 'tis ſuggeſted.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>the Jeſuits are for free Prayer in Publick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That <hi>Free Prayer is the Jeſuits invention;</hi> If this be not the ſcope of the inſinuation, to what purpoſe is it mentioned? But if it be, I will evince out of the Jeſuits own writings, that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Free Prayer to be known by the <hi>Fathers;</hi> and that they allow it only its private Exerciſe, even as others of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Faction; and the Doctor himſelf, &amp;c. do.<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Azorius Moral. inſti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi> Illud vero Pauli; ipſe Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus poſtulat pro nobis. <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> in lib. de bono Perſever. <hi>c. 23.</hi> interpretatur. <hi>q</hi> Poftulat, <hi>q</hi> Poſtulare nos docet, aut facit, quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum illud, <hi>Matth. 10.</hi> quod dixit Chriſtus Apoſtolis. Non vos eſtis qui loquimini, ſed Spiritus Patris veſtri, qui loquitur in vobis, non quod verè loquatur, ſed quod ad verum loquendum vim, facultatem, auxilium &amp; gratiam largiatur, ſic Poſtulat, quia poſtulandi, &amp; orandi vim, &amp; poteſtatem tribuit &amp; facit ut poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemus. Et it a <hi>Auguſtinum</hi> ſecuti explicant Paulum eo Loco <hi>Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Beda, Anſelmus,</hi> ut etiam <hi>Sedulius. Fulgentus</hi> Epiſt. ad Probam de Omit. &amp; Compunct. Cord. Et quia frequenter a nobis of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenditur, neceſſarium eſt, ut frequenti Oratione, &amp; jugi Cordis compunctione, mitigetur. Compunctio enim cordis excitat Orationis affectum: Oratio hunnlis, divinum promeretur Auxilium. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punctio cordis vulnera ſua reſpicit: Oratio vero, med<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Sanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis exp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſuit. Et <hi>ad haec quis idoneus? Quis enim vel orare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petenter valeat;</hi> niſi Medicus ipſe nobis initium <hi>deſiderii Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualis</hi> infundat? Aut quis Purſeverare in Oratione queat: niſi Deus in nobis hoc quod caepit, augeat. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Azorius</hi> the <q>Jeſuit expreſſeth himſelf thus moſt freely <hi>vid.</hi> That of <hi>Paul,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49455:9"/>Rom.</hi> 8.26. Where 'tis ſaid, the Spirit maketh interceſſion for us, <hi>Saint Austin</hi> in <hi>lib. de bono Perſever: c.</hi> 23 Doth interpret it thus, the Spirit teacheth us to pray, or maketh interceſſion according to that expreſſion in <hi>Math.</hi> 10.20. for it is not ye that ſpeak, but the Spirit of your Father, which ſpeaketh in you, not that the <hi>Spirit</hi> doth <hi>truly,</hi> or properly ſpeak, but that it vouchſafeth the Power, Help or Grace to ſpeak the Truth, even ſo the <hi>Spirit prayeth,</hi> becauſe it giveth out the <hi>Power,</hi> and Grace of Prayer. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> is as to this followed by <hi>Primaſius, Bede, Anſelme, and Sedulius,</hi> ſo far <hi>Azorius.</hi> But I will add, and by <hi>Fulgentus,</hi> who ſaith becauſe we frequently of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God by our ſins, 'tis neceſſary that we often by Prayer and compunction of Soul attempt the pleaſing him. Compunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of heart ſtirreth up the affection of Prayer, and an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayer obtains Divine Aſſiſtance, Compunction of Heart reſpects our Wounds, Prayer ſeeketh for a Remedy; but who is ſufficient for theſe things, or who can pray as he ought unleſs the <hi>Phiſitian himſelf infuſe into us the beginnings of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual prayer?</hi> or who can perſevere in Prayer unleſs God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in us what he hath began.</q> I might inſtance in many others, but this is enough to ſhew that <hi>Spiritual Prayer</hi> is not owing unto the Jeſuits for its Invention or Diſcovery; and therefore I will proceed to inform the Dr. that the Publick Exerciſe, of <hi>Free Prayer,</hi> is not approved off by the Jeſuits, For as concerning publick prayer the Jeſuits do differ from the Diſſenters if not from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> agreeing with none that I know unleſs with other papiſts and with <hi>Dr. Stil.</hi> for though
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49455:9"/>
                  <hi>private</hi> and <hi>Free Prayers</hi> are with <hi>Azorius</hi> and other Jeſuits terms promiſcuouſly uſed to expreſs one, and the ſame thing, yet <hi>publick Prayer</hi> muſt be according to <hi>ſome certain preſcribed form,</hi> This is the ſenſe of <hi>(Vincent Fillincius,)</hi> yea of <hi>(Bellarmine)</hi> and before him of <hi>(Durandus,)</hi> it being proved by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> to be thus appointed by the Milevitane Council <hi>Can.</hi> 12. yea by the Toletan, 4. <hi>c,</hi> 2. and by <hi>Pope Gregory. &amp;c</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being ſo the Dr's <hi>miſtakes</hi> are apparent, and the Truth is.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Jeſuits were not the firſt inventors, nor the firſt bringers in of <hi>Spiritual Prayer, Spiritual Prayer</hi> being owned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and privately practiſed ever ſince the Apoſtles dayes, for the Church never did for bid its uſe ſaith <hi>Fillincius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Jeſuits ever have, and ſtill do zealouſly oppoſe the <hi>Publick uſe of Free Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 That wherein the Jeſuits, and Diſſenters agree as to this, it is in no other reſpect then wherein the Univerſal Church agree with them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That wherein the Diſſenters and the <hi>Dr.</hi> differ about <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Dr.</hi> cloſeth with the Jeſuit, our difference if any being about the publick uſe of Spiritual Prayer againſt which the Jeſuits are.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>2. <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Diſſenters have blaſted the Reputation and honour of the firſt Reformation, which is the great thing the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> would<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Fillincius Tract. Quſt. Moral Ttract. <hi>23.</hi> c. <hi>3,</hi> N. <hi>67.6.8.</hi> de <hi>Bellarm.</hi> de bon. oper. impartic. lib. <hi>1 c. 10.</hi> nemo enim poteſt <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam formam orandi</hi> preſcribere, niſi qui praeeſt. Itaque in Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio Milevitano, can. <hi>12.</hi> Sic legimus: Placuit, ut Preces, Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, ſeu Miſſae, quae probatae fuerint in Concilio, ab omnibus cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brentur. <hi>Nec aliae omnino dicantur in Eccleſia,</hi> niſi <hi>quae a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentioribus tractatae,</hi> vel <hi>comprobatae</hi> in <hi>ſynodo fuerint.</hi> Et in Concilio <hi>Toletano. IV. c. 2.</hi> Statuitur ut in tota Provincia <hi>idem officium celebretur.</hi> Et <hi>Gregorius Papa VII.</hi> in Concilio generali numerum Pſalmorum, &amp; Lectionum officii Divini praeſcripſit, ut ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur. Can. In die, de conſecratione. diſt. <hi>5.</hi> c Durant. in ſent. lib. <hi>4.</hi> diſt q. <hi>15.12.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49455:10"/>be at, for ſaith the Dr. Preface, p. 9. <hi>What is it which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have more envied, and maligned than the</hi> Church of England? <hi>What is it they have more wiſhed to ſee broken in pieces? that is, than the Conſtitution and</hi> Government <hi>of this Church? Did not</hi> Cranmer, Ridley, <hi>and</hi> Hooper, <hi>and</hi> Farrar, <hi>and</hi> Latimer, <hi>all</hi> Biſhops <hi>of this</hi> Church, <hi>ſuffer</hi> Martyrdom <hi>by their Means? Had not they the ſame kind of Epiſcopacy which is now among us, and which ſome now are ſo buſie in ſeeking to deſtroy.—Is all this done for the Honour of the</hi> Reformation? <hi>Is this the way to preſerve the Proteſtant Religion among us, to fill mens minds with ſuch prejudices againſt the firſt ſettlement of it: to go about to make the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Church Government then eſtabliſhed, was</hi> repugnant <hi>to the</hi> inſtitution <hi>of Chriſt, and that our</hi> Martyr-Biſhops <hi>exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an unlawful Authority over</hi> Dioceſan Churches? <hi>Such men do the Jeſuits work for them as effectually, as if they had been ſet on work by them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In anſwer, it muſt be carefully obſerved that the Papiſts do not ſo much envy, and maligne the Epiſcopal Government, 'tis the Drs. <hi>miſtake,</hi> for the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> or the Engliſh <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> is not ſo formidable a thing in a Jeſuits Eye; neither is it their <hi>principle</hi> or <hi>Intereſt</hi> to deſtroy it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not their <hi>principle,</hi> which is for the conſerving <hi>Epiſcopal Government,</hi> for
<list>
                     <item>1. The Papiſts plead moſt zealouſly for that difference, there is ſaid by the Church of England to be between a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and a <hi>Preſbyter,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. They deny the peoples right of calling their own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</item>
                     <item>3. Aſſert that the Church hath power to inſtitute new Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. They do <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> between a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and a <hi>Preſbyter,</hi> and with the Church of England aſſert, that the <hi>Catholick Church doth acknowledge</hi> a diſtinction to be between a Biſhop and a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, and that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is <hi>jure divino,</hi> greater than a <hi>Preſbyter;</hi> and this <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and the <hi>Romiſh</hi> faction inſiſt on in oppoſition to the <hi>Reform'd,</hi> namely in oppoſition to <hi>Wickliff,</hi> the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> and <hi>Calveniſts,</hi> whence they go on with the greateſt malice againſt the Proteſtants; to the end they may <hi>Haereticate</hi> and damn every Soul among 'em, and ſay that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> only hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49455:10"/>power to ordain, and that if any be ordained by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> that <hi>Ordination</hi> is null, which is according to that of <hi>Gregory</hi> III in his Epiſtle to <hi>Boniface,</hi> from which they proceed, as I ſhall ſhew immediately) to deny the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calveniſts</hi> to be true Churches for want of the right Adminiſtration of Sacraments, that is the product of the want of true Miniſters, or which is the ſame, becauſe they have not Miniſters Epiſcopally ordained, ſo<note n="f" place="bottom">Bel. de Cleric. lib. 1. c. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Whereby it appears that the papiſts are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this part of the Prelacy of Biſhops.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the People have no Intereſt in the <hi>Vocation,</hi> or cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their own Miniſters, is alſo the <hi>Principle</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For<note n="g" place="bottom">Bellarm. de Cleric. lib. 1. c. 2. &amp;c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in ſtating this point, ſaith, that the Controverſie between them and their Adverſaries, to wit the Reformed, is about the Right of Creating <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Presbyters</hi> in the Church, and he aſſerts that <hi>Martin Luther, John Calvin, Mat Illyricus, Brentius, Chemnitius,</hi> and others of the <hi>Sectaries, i.e.</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> do hold, That no one is Lawfully called, or choſen to the Office of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> but by the conſent and ſuffrage of the People, and therefore they infer (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>) that there are no Biſhops or Paſtors among the Papiſts <hi>rightly</hi> called, for want of the ſuffrage of the People: But on the other ſide, the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> concludes, that the <hi>people have no right to call their Miniſters,</hi> and that although the People did formerly chooſe their own Miniſters, it was through the Conceſſion or Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Popes. And therefore they ſay that the Hereticks, or the Proteſtants have no true Miniſtry, no right Adminiſtration of Sacraments, no Church, no Salvation, (for <hi>extra Eccleſiam nullaſalus.</hi>) The Reaſons they give againſt the Peoples Election beſides many others, are theſe; drawn</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. From the Indiſcretion of the People, and conſequently their inability to judge of the Capacity of the Perſon to be Choſen.</item>
                  <item>2. The greater Number of the people are Fooliſh, and the viler ſort, and conſequently-will chooſe men like themſelves.</item>
                  <item>3. Such a practice is obnoxious and liable unto ſad Tumults, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Not remembering that the <hi>people,</hi> who are to chooſe, muſt be conſidered as <hi>men fearing God,</hi> and that there is care taken that the perſon to be Choſen is out of ſuch a number, as are by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49455:11"/>the <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>Judicious</hi> approv'd of, as men of Competent Abilities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this alſo the Principles of the Jeſuites are far from deſtroying the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="3">3. That the Church hath power to inſtitute new<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Bel. de effect. Sacram. lib. 2. c. 29.</hi> Quaedam caeremoniae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituuntur ad ſolum ornatum &amp; ſignificationem, ut veſtis alba Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phytorum, Lumina cercorum, &amp;c. &amp; de his agimus. — <hi>c. 30</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temur enimomnes Catholici Caeremonias Eccleſiaſticas non eſſe praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puum cultum; nec ab iis pendere eſſentiam &amp; eſſicaciam ſacramento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: nec habere vim Juſtificandi, ut habent ſacramenta, proinde inferiora eſſe ſacramentis, nec eſſe approbandos ritus qui pugnant cum verbo Dei, nec eſſe nimis multiplicandos. Et <hi>cap. 31.</hi> Sed quicquid de hoc ſit: noſtra propoſitio ſolum aſſerit contra haereticos, licere Eccleſiae inſtituere novas caeremonias non ad juſtificandum a peccatis mortalibus ſed ad alios fines.—Omnes noſtrae caeremoniae ſunt bonae &amp; divinae: nam indicantur in <hi>genere</hi> a Deo &amp; probantur multis modis <hi>1.</hi> In ipſo teſtimonio Pauli, <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>14.</hi> Omnia honeſte, &amp;c: 2. Cum Deus jubet obediri praepoſitis, in genere jubet ſervari omnes leges Eccleſiaſticas, quorum non paucae ſunt de caeremoniis.</note> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which Aſſertion they thus limit.
<list>
                     <item>1. Not ſuch Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as are repugnant to the Word of God;</item>
                     <item>but 2. Such as are generally contain'd in that Scripture, Let all things be done decently and in order, and that they are not to be preferred to the Sacraments, nor muſt the ſame efficacy be attributed unto them; they only aſſert againſt the Hereticks, that 'tis lawful for the Church to inſtitute new Ceremonies, not for Juſtification but for other ends.</item>
                  </list> The white Garment being for Ornament and Signification. All this <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is expreſs in, and therefore not againſt this part of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> That I abuſe not the <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> nor <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> will ſoon appear to ſuch as will but ſeriouſly conſult the ſenſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> who are expreſs in aſſerting all this and much more; namely, that as the <hi>Decency</hi> of the Ceremonies is one Reaſon why we muſt obſerve them, ſo our <hi>Superiours</hi> Command is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Thus the Principles of the Jeſuits, and other Papiſts being ſo much for a Prelatical Epiſcopacy, ſo much againſt the peoples Choice, and ſo much for Ceremonies with the mention'd Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, how is it poſſible that the Dr. preſum'd to aſſert that the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49455:11"/>Papiſts aim at the deſtruction of what they too much contend for againſt the Generality of our Reformed Divines? But<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not the <hi>Intereſt of the Jeſuites</hi> to <hi>deſtroy Epiſcopacy,</hi> or eradicate the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and thereby break the Conſtitution of this Government. 'Tis probable they would add unto the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, but the deſtroying it they abhor. For,
<list>
                     <item>1. A great part of their bait would be loſt, if Epiſcopacy be ruin'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What more evident than that the Papiſts aim at our Biſhopricks; not at the deſtroying them, but at the poſſeſſing themſelves of them. 'Tis the <hi>Epiſcopal Grandeur, Church Honours,</hi> and <hi>Church Lands</hi> that they would be at.</item>
                     <item>2. The Jeſuits know, that 'tis much more eaſie to introduce their Religion under the <hi>ſhadow,</hi> and <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and Ceremonies than otherwiſe. What difficulty is there in drawing the vulgar to the whole of Popery, under pretences of a more firm eſtabliſhing Epiſcopacy, and a making the Ceremony the more ſplendid and ſolemn.</item>
                     <item>3. May there not be an alteration in our Doctrines, when no alteration in our Government; and might not the Papiſts gain greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by their being made <hi>Biſhops,</hi> than by the Ruine of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. It is not dangerous to break Conſtitutions, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſince the deſtruction of Epiſcopacy may be attended with the <hi>Royal diſtribution</hi> of Church Lands among our <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> than which a greater blow cannot be given the <hi>Papal</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in <hi>England,</hi> as appears by the <hi>Heroick</hi> actings of <hi>Henry the 8th.</hi> in a like Caſe.</item>
                  </list> Are not the Papiſts ſenſible of this? What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Dr. may think, there are the higheſt Reaſons to ingage us to conclude that the Jeſuits dread nothing more than the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Epiſcopacy and the removal of the Ceremonies.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. That the <hi>Reputation of the firſt Reformation is not hereby blaſted,</hi> nor are the <hi>firſt Reformers</hi> in the leaſt <hi>Reproached</hi> But<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. The memory of theſe Worthies, namely, <hi>Cranmer, Ridley,</hi> and <hi>Hooper,</hi> &amp;c. is precious unto the <hi>diſſenters,</hi> who can diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between their Epiſcopacy and their Martyrdom, they not being Martyr'd for Epiſcopacy but for renouncing tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c. They ſealed thoſe Truths with their blood unto which the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> deſire to give in their Teſtimony, in abiding by them faithful to the Death.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe famous Martyrs we honour, yea and the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> they carried on, it being a wonder, that in leſs than <hi>ſix years</hi> time, they ſhould do more towards Reformation than all the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49455:12"/>
                  <hi>Biſhops in England</hi> beſides have done in almoſt ſix ſcore years, They went as far as poſſibly they could in that juncture, and probably would have gone <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>paſſu</hi> with <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> &amp;c. had they the time and opportunity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I find in the Report of the Examination of <hi>William Nixon,</hi> had the 20th. day of <hi>June, Anno,</hi> 1567. before the Lord <hi>Mayor,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Nixon</hi> gives this following anſwer to the like objection made then by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> which is moſt pat to this of the Doctor. <q>We condemn them not, we ſhould go forward unto Perfection, for we have had the Goſpel along time among us. And the beſt of them that did maintain it, did <hi>recant</hi> it at their Death, as did <hi>Ridley,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Taylor. Ridley</hi> did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his fault to <hi>Hooper,</hi> and when they would have put on him the ſame <hi>Apparel,</hi> he ſaid they were abominable, and too fond for a vice in Play.</q> Which is ſufficient to evince, that if theſe Biſhops had outlived the <hi>Marian Perſecution,</hi> they would have gone on towards a greater Reformation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. 'Tis very conſiderable, that thoſe very Perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who were ſo zealous in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days for Epiſcopacy, were perſons of whom 'tis recorded.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That in the time of Perſecution they were men of the ſame Principles with Diſſenters.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That after the Perſecution was over, they did proceed with the ſmarteſt Proſecution of Laws againſt them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That in the time of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Biſhops were of the ſame Principles with the Diſſenters concerning Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for this conſult the Letter of Mr. <hi>D. Wy,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten about the Year 1570. who ſaith, <q>That ſuch Biſhops as fled in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> time, or elſe tarried here under the Croſs; had caſt off, renounced and forſaken all this Trumpery, <hi>i. e.</hi> (the Ceremonies) for the which the Peace is now diſturbed, and afterward for their promotion ſake put them on again. The like in a Letter written by Mr. <hi>A. G.</hi> to Mr. <hi>Coverdale, Turner,</hi> &amp;c. who ſpeaking of the Ceremonies, ſaith, That all theſe things were abhor'd, as <hi>Popiſh</hi> Superſtition and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try among the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Goſpellers, both <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>others;</hi> when they were under <hi>Gods Rod</hi> in Poverty: But they have now learned <hi>Courtly Divinity,</hi> to ground all upon Policy.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>That <hi>when theſe very men were raiſed to Honour, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49455:12"/>to be very <hi>ſevere</hi> in perſecuting their <hi>Brethren,</hi> and their <hi>quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam fellow-ſifterers,</hi> the Diſſenters Yea, to diſcover greater en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt them, than againſt the <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
                  </q> This may be ſeen in a Letter of Dr. <hi>Wy.</hi> 
                  <q>They ſay they would that all <hi>Traſh</hi> and <hi>Trumpery</hi> were out of the Church, [meaning the Ceremonies] and yet they ſtretch the utter moſt piece of their Authority to the keeping of it. And a little after 'tis ſaid, 'I could rehearſe by Name a <hi>Biſhops</hi> boy, ruffainly both in behaviour and apparel, at every word ſwearing and ſtaring, having <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, a worthy prebend, no doubt: I could name <hi>Whoremongers</hi> being taking, and alſo confeſſing their <hi>Letchery,</hi> and yet both enjoying <hi>their Livings,</hi> and alſo having their Mouths open, not ſtopped, not forbidden to Preach. I know alſo ſome, that have ſaid <hi>Maſs divers years,</hi> ſince it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited, and upon their Examination confeſſed the ſame, and yet are in quiet poſſeſſion of their Eccleſiaſtical promotions. I know <hi>double-beneficed</hi> men, that do nothing but eat, drink, ſleep, play at Dice, Cards, Tables, Bowls, and read Service in the Church; but theſe infect not their Flocks with falſe Doctrine, for they teach nothing at all.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thus it is evident, that Gods Commandments are fain to give place to mans traditions; and yet ſtill all theſe are but ſmall matters. Verily the puniſhment is great I wonder what puniſhment they would uſe, if they had tranſgreſſors of great matters in handling, that deal after this ſort with ſuch as offend (and yet offend not at all) but as they ſay, in ſuch ſmall matters.</q> But this muſt not be mentioned, leaſt the Honour of the firſt Reformation be blaſted, that is, the Diſſenters muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not only unto the greateſt ſeverities with all manner of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; but moreover, though Gods Truths be neglected, and a ſinful Miniſtry countenanced, they muſt remain in ſilence, leaſt the reputation of theſe men be blaſted. That ſurely muſt be the meaning of the blaſting the Reformation. But</p>
               <p n="5">5. Notwithſtanding the ſeverity exerciſed againſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diſſenters; even when the Papiſts eſcaped the ſmartneſs of the Law, yet it is obſervable, that the <hi>Queens Council,</hi> whoſew <hi>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>firmneſs</hi> to the Proteſtant Religion hath been renowned all the World over, did then diſcover themſelves to <hi>judge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe</hi> of the Diſſenters, than the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> did, yea, although the Biſhops were then very baſie in turning the dege of thoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49455:13"/>Laws that were deſigned for Papiſts, againſt Diſſenters; Yet that <hi>wiſe Council</hi> did diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and thereby plainly diſcover, that the Diſſenters <hi>there,</hi> were far from carrying on the Popiſh deſign, as appears by <hi>their</hi> Letter ſent to their Juſtices on the complaint of the Diſſenters, made to the Right Honourable Lords of Her Majeſties Privy Council.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Copy of which Letter ſent from the Right Honourable the Lords of Her Majeſties Council, I will as I find it in a part of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter inſert.</head>
                     <p>AFter Our very hearty Commendations; whereas we are informed, that heretofore, at your <hi>Aſſizes</hi> in your Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit divers good Preachers, and others Godly diſpoſed, have been indicted (by <hi>colour</hi> of Law,) for things not ſo much againſt the matter and very <hi>meaning</hi> of the Law, as in ſome <hi>ſhew,</hi> ſwearv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Letter thereof; Namely, for not <hi>uſing the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſs,</hi> reſorting to Sermons in other Pariſhes, for want at home; leaving out ſome collects on the dayes of Preaching, for uſing <hi>private Prayer</hi> in their houſes, and ſuch like. All which we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe cometh to paſs by the practice of ſome <hi>Informers,</hi> not ſo <hi>well diſpoſed in Religion,</hi> as alſo of men returned upon great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. Many times ſuch as be ſtill in Ignorance cannot broke the Goſpel, and being in love with the Licence of former times, cannot ſo well indure the preſent plain Teachers; who by laying open their faults, would draw them to a more preciſe, and Goſpel-like Life. Theſe are therefore to <hi>require you,</hi> and <hi>hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to pray</hi> you, that in every ſitting of your Circuit, you ſift and examine the <hi>affection</hi> of ſuch Informers, touching <hi>Religion,</hi> and thereafter give ear to them. As alſo to have a ſpecial regard, That the <hi>Inqueſt</hi> at large may be <hi>Religions, wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Honeſt:</hi> And if (notwithſtanding your diligence in this behalf,) ſuch <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi> (nevertheleſs) creep in (as by like information moleſt <hi>good men</hi>) that yet your ſpeech, and whole proceedins againſt them at the Bar, (or elſewhere called before you) may be according to their <hi>quality:</hi> not <hi>watching them at bar,</hi> or in the <hi>inditement</hi> with <hi>Rogues, Fellons</hi> or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but rather giving <hi>apparent note</hi> (in the Face of the Countrey) what <hi>difference</hi> you hold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Papiſts</hi> (<hi>diſſenting from us</hi> in the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>Faith to God,</hi>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49455:13"/>and <hi>Loyalty</hi> to our <hi>Prince</hi>) and theſe <hi>other men,</hi> which <hi>making ſome Conſcience</hi> of theſe <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> do yet <hi>diligently,</hi> and <hi>ſoundly Preach</hi> true Religion, and <hi>obedience to her Majeſly: maintaining</hi> the <hi>Common peace</hi> in themſelves. and in their <hi>Auditory;</hi> ſo ſhall the Countrey thereby learn (at the Aſſizes) better to reverence the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and love the <hi>Miniſters</hi> and Profeſſors thereof. Thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing our ſelves thus much at your hands, we bid you heartily Farewell, From, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Thus you have the ſence of Q. <hi>Eli.</hi> Council, and may have the like ſence from our Parliament now.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being ſo, let the Impartial Reader judge who it is that hath blaſted the Reputation of the firſt Reformation.</p>
               <p>Whether
<list>
                     <item>1. Thoſe that remained faithful to theſe Principles of the Martyrs and other Proteſtant ſufferers in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, or thoſe that receeded from them.</item>
                     <item>2. Thoſe that hazarded the loſs of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Benefices for the ſake of Proteſtant Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, or thoſe that perſecuted the Proteſtants, when the debauched Papiſts were favoured by them.</item>
                     <item>3. Thoſe that would carry on the Reformation as far as <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and the generality of the firſt Reformers, or thoſe that gratified the Papiſts, by putting a ſtop to ſo Goſpel-like a procedure, revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius,</hi> as <hi>German</hi>-Drunkards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as ſome of the Epiſcopal Clergy did in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths dayes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. They who acknowledge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a true Church, having a Miniſtry rightly, <hi>i. e.</hi> Epiſcopally ordained, when all the Reformed beyond the Seas, are reproached for want of it, or Thoſe who concur with the Reformed.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>3. <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Diſſenters oppoſe <hi>Epiſcopacy and Innocent Ceremonies,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their <hi>Antiquity.</hi> 
                  <q>'Tis aſſerted by the Dr. <hi>Pref</hi> p. 4, 5. That when the People find the undoubted practices of the <hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church condemned</hi> as Popiſh and Antichriſtian by their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; they muſt conclude Popery to be of much greater <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49455:14"/>then really it is; and when they can trace it ſo very near the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times,</hi> they will ſoon believe it ſetled by the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For it will be very hard to perſwade any conſidering men, that the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church ſhould <hi>degenerate</hi> ſo <hi>ſoon,</hi> ſo <hi>unammouſly,</hi> ſo <hi>univerſally,</hi> as it muſt do, if <hi>Epiſcopal Government,</hi> and the uſe of ſome ſignificant Ceremonies were any parts of that <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> Will it not ſeem ſtrange to them, that when ſome humane policies have preſerved their <hi>firſt Conſtitution</hi> ſo long, without any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Alteration, that the Goverment inſtituted by Chriſt, and ſettled by his Apoſtles, ſhould ſo ſoon after be changed into <hi>another kind,</hi> and that ſo <hi>eaſily,</hi> ſo <hi>inſenſibly,</hi> that all the Chriſtian Churches believed, they had ſtill the very ſame Government, which the Apoſtles left e'm; Which is a matter ſo incredible, that thoſe who can believe ſuch a part of Popery ſhould prevail ſo ſoon in the Chriſtian Church, may be brought upon the <hi>like</hi> Grounds to believe, that many others did. So mighty a <hi>prejudice</hi> doth the <hi>Principles</hi> of our Churches Enemies, bring upon the cauſe of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Anſwer,</hi> There are theſe things to be diſtinctly conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether the not embracing the</hi> Epiſcopacy <hi>doth any way advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage the</hi> Papiſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether there is any ſuch ſtrength to be found in the Drs: reaſoning. Firſt, From the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> And Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, From the <hi>Argument</hi> produc'd to prove its Antiquity, to wit, the <hi>Improbability</hi> of introducing <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ninſtituted Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> into the Church without ſome <hi>noiſe</hi> and clamour. I ſay, Whether there is any ſuch ſtrength in theſe reaſonings, that none can oppoſe them, without giving too great an advantage unto the Papiſt.</p>
               <p>To the firſt, Namely, Whether the non-embracing <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> doth any way advantage the Papiſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From what hath been already ſaid, 'Tis ſufficiently proved, that the non-embracing Epiſcopacy doth rather <hi>prejudice</hi> then <hi>profit</hi> the Papal intereſt; for which Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When attempts have been made by <hi>Franciſe. a Sancta Clara</hi> for the accommodating the differences between the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Church of England,</hi> he ever with indignation excepts againſt the <hi>Puritane,</hi> as a people no way reconcileable to their Church, yea, when he proves it eaſie to heal the breach between them, and the Epiſcopal.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49455:14"/>
               <p>Moreover, 3. Whoever conſults<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Becan,</hi> opus. Tit. <hi>10.</hi> Calviniſtae in <hi>Scotia</hi> &amp; <hi>Anglia</hi> vocantur Puritani quia puram <hi>Calvini</hi> Doctrinam per omnia ſequuntur.</note> 
                  <hi>Becanus</hi> the Jeſuite, will find; how he ſeems to honour the <hi>Church of England,</hi> by giving credit to the reports they make againſt the <hi>Puritans</hi> (who are ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Jeſuit, becauſe they embrace the <hi>pure Doctrine of</hi> Calvine) to the end they may thereby from the mouths of ſome Proteſtants, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> condemn all the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches abroad, the Jeſuits malice being the more inflam'd to ſee ſo many Diſſenters in <hi>England,</hi> that juſtifie the <hi>Reformation</hi> made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Doctors diſcourſe about the <hi>Antiquity of Epiſcopacy;</hi> and the argument enforcing it, muſt needs be of great weight with the Doctor, it having been for divers years a furbiſhing in the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits School; and is the <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church at this very time, the great <hi>foundation,</hi> and <hi>Baſis</hi> of that tottering Superſtructure, this is their only <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> their firſt and the laſt, whence if the Reformed oppoſe their <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> their <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> their Inventions, their Corruptions; this is that unto which they ſlie, <hi>tanquam ad Aſylum, viz.</hi> Theſe things muſt be Apoſtolical, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis impoſſible they ſhould be introduced into the Church without any noiſe. Really the Doctor hath done this argument the greateſt honour imaginable, but whether the Church of <hi>England</hi> are owing unto him for this piece of ſervice, I much doubt. That this is<note n="†" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Bellar.</hi> de notis Eccleſ. lib. <hi>4. c. 5.</hi> In omni inſigni <hi>mutatione</hi> Religionis ſemper iſta ſex demonſtrari poſſunt. Primo Auctor ejus. <hi>II.</hi> Dogma aliquod novum. <hi>III.</hi> Tempus quo caepit. <hi>IV. Locus ubi</hi> caepit. <hi>V.</hi> Quis eam oppugnaverit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — Nihil autem horum adverſarii unquam de noſtra Eccleſia post <hi>Apoſtolica tempora</hi> demonſtrare potue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. — Nunquam oſtenderunt, quis eam oppugnaverint, tamquam nuper ortam. — Hoc argumentum ab <hi>Antiquitate</hi> ſemper uſi ſunt veteres Patres contra Haereticos ad oſtendendam veram Eccleſiam.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s <hi>Thunderbolt</hi> againſt the Hereticks, conſult him, and you will find him exactly ſo. To rehearſe the many Arguments produced by the Reformed in beating down this <hi>Popiſh Errour,</hi> would be endleſs, whoever reads any learned Proteſtant cannot but be furniſhed with a multitude of Convincing Conſiderations, that are urg'd againſt this Doctors Argument.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49455:15"/>
               <p n="1">1. Nothing being more apparent, then that the Scriptures of the New Teſtament, the Antienteſt Writings the Chriſtian Church can produce, as the infallible diſcovery of the firſt <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Churches,</hi> how ancient ſoever Epiſcopacy or Ceremonies are, if not to be found in the New Teſtament. It is not the <hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> or <hi>firſt Conſtitution.</hi> This is our Religion, and whoever receeds from it, doth but give too great advantage unto the Papiſt, there being ſeveral Ceremonies in uſe among them, whoſe <hi>Antiquity</hi> doth equalize that of any obſerv'd by our Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis well known, that if we had the fulleſt account of the <hi>Riſe</hi> of Epiſcopacy and Ceremonies, as to the <hi>time</hi> when, the <hi>place</hi> where, the <hi>Perſons</hi> by whom they were introduced, our Faith could not thereby be more Divine concerning theſe things than now it is, for the Teſtimony would be but <hi>Humane,</hi> grounding a Faith that is only ſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We have a very ſhort account of the tranſactions of the firſt 300 years, the perſecution of the Churches being ſo ſevere and bloody, which is enough to evince, (becauſe of the inconſiſtency of Epiſcopal grandeur with a perſecuted ſtate,) that neither Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, nor pompous Ceremonies were then in their Glory.</p>
               <p>Again,</p>
               <p n="4">4. 'Tis certain that thoſe Errours creept in <hi>gradually,</hi> the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity being a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> that began even in the Apoſtles days, and I remember that I have read in the Annals of <hi>Said Ibn. Batrick,</hi> an <hi>Alexandrian Patriarch,</hi> who lived about 200 years after the <hi>Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Hegyra,</hi> that in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the Conſtitution <hi>gradually alter'd,</hi> firſt from <hi>Presbyters</hi> to a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and thence to a <hi>Pope,</hi> though not to an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal One.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it not then ſad, that there muſt not be an urging Proteſtant arguments againſt the Antiquity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pretended by the Papiſts, but Popery is advantag'd? What advantage is it to them to ſee the Temple of their <hi>Diana</hi> ruin'd, their City of refuge demoliſhed? I beſeech the Doctor to be ſerious in this weighty and momentous point, and to deal freely, openly and generouſly in this particular, and declare unto the World what his apprehenſions are of Dr. <hi>Potter,</hi> ſometimes Biſhop of <hi>Carlile,</hi> or rather of the Learned Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> a Son of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whoſe excellent treatiſe entituled <hi>The Religion of Proteſtants, a ſafe way to Salvation,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo applauded by Dr. <hi>Bayly,</hi> ſometime <hi>Vice-Chancellor</hi> of <hi>Oxjord;</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49455:15"/>as alſo by Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> and Dr. <hi>S. Fell;</hi> or rather what would the Dr. rejoyn unto the Anſwer that is found in Mr. <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llingworth,</hi> unto his great Argument about <hi>Antiquity</hi> and the <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> of an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's becoming <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> in ſo ſhort a time. <q>Though ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants confeſs (ſaith Mr. <hi>C.</hi> to the Papiſts) ſome of your Doctrines to be antient, ſo long as it is evident, even by the Confeſſion of all ſides, that many Errors, I inſtance in that of the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> and the <hi>communicating of Infants,</hi> were more Antient. Not any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity therefore, unleſs it be <hi>abſolute,</hi> and <hi>Primitive,</hi> is a certain ſign of true Doctrine. For, if the Church were obnoxious to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption (as we pretend it was) who can poſſibly warrant us that part of this Corruption might not get in and prevail in the 5th, or 4th. or 3d. or 2d. Age?</q> [This notwithſtanding what Dr. <hi>Stil.</hi> doth ſuggeſt about the near approach unto the Apoſtles dayes.] <q>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſeeing the Apoſtles aſſure us, that the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> was working though more ſecretly even intheir times. If any man ask how could it become <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> in ſo <hi>ſhort a time?</hi>
                  </q> [Attend good Dr. to the anſwer for this is your own Queſtion] Let him tell <q>me how the errour of the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> and the Communicating of Infants, became ſo <hi>ſoon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> and then he ſhall acknowledge, what was done in ſome, was <hi>poſſible</hi> in others.</q> Thus we ſee how Dr. <hi>Stil.</hi> to the end he may be even with the Diſſenters relinquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the good old Proteſtant Principles, unleſs this of Mr. <hi>Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> approved of by Dr. <hi>Baily,</hi> Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Fell,</hi> and the generality of the Church of <hi>England</hi> be <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>'Our Diviſions give great advantage to the Papiſts; and the 'Diſſenters by their Separation have caus'd the Diviſion.</p>
               <p>To this I Reply,</p>
               <p n="1">I. That 'tis moſt apparent that Diviſions among Proteſtants have given the greateſt advantages imaginable unto Popery; as to this, the Dr. and the Diſſenters I verily believe, are agreed. But,</p>
               <p n="2">II. The great Quaery is, <hi>who occaſions, or cauſeth theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions?</hi> for 'tis the <hi>Divider</hi> onely, that is ſubſervient to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49455:16"/>
                  <hi>Roman</hi> Intereſt, which being ſo, our enquiry muſt be, Whether the Dr. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are the Dividers?</p>
               <p>The Dr. ſuggeſts as if the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy</hi> were moſt entirely reſolv'd for Union, but 'tis the <hi>Diſſenter</hi> that is the divider, who is an Enemy to Union, but a Friend to Schiſm, and U<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>juſt Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <q>We were (ſaith the Dr.) in ſome hopes, that Men ſo <hi>wiſe,</hi> as the Non-conforming Miniſters repreſent themſelves to the World, would in ſo <hi>Critical</hi> a time have made ſome ſteps or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances towards an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with us. Inſtead of this, theſe we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed with, ſeemed farther off than before. For (ſaith the Dr.) God forbid that I ſhould either deſign, or do any thing which tended to obſtruct ſo bleſſed a work, as a <hi>Firm</hi> and <hi>Laſting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> among Proteſtants would be. But my buſineſs is to ſhew the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of thoſe Principles</hi> and <hi>Practiſes,</hi> which hinder men from ſuch an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and lay a <hi>Foundation</hi> for <hi>perpetual</hi> and <hi>endleſs Separations.</hi> For upon the <hi>Principles</hi> laid down by ſome of our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren,</hi> let the Conſtitution be made never ſo <hi>eaſie</hi> to themſelves, yet others may make uſe of their grounds, and carry on the difference as high as ever. Which will render all attempts of Union Vain; and leave the ſame weapons ready to be taken up by others.</q>
               </p>
               <p>So far the Dr's <hi>Miſtakes,</hi> which in theſe few words, are many. For,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Diſſenters are at this time as much for Union according to the Terms of the Goſpel as any can reaſonably deſire. 'Tis for <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> they breath, and Pray, and moſt induſtriouſly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely endeavour, being engag'd hereunto by Intereſt; for as long as Diviſions continue, they are expos'd to the worſt of Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are moſt admirably ſuited for a firm and laſting Union with all ſuch as will adhere to the Terms pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Goſpel.</item>
                  <item>3. 'Tis the Dr. that falls in with <hi>Bellarmine</hi> giving the Papiſts the greateſt encouragment to an abiding by their perſecuting Principles, even when he diſſents from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. 'Tis the Dr. that hath done his utmoſt to <hi>obſtruct</hi> a <hi>firm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> among <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>That all this, to the Satisfaction of the <hi>Judicious,</hi> and <hi>impartial Reader,</hi> may be evinced, I will propoſe in ſhort the true <hi>ſtate</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49455:16"/>of the Controverſie, ſo far as I apprehend it; and then detect the Dr's Miſtakes, as to thoſe but now mention'd particulars.</p>
               <p>In giving the <hi>ſtate</hi> of this Controverſie, I muſt intimate where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is an <hi>agreement;</hi> and wherein the <hi>Difference</hi> doth lie.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We are <hi>agreed</hi> in <hi>Doctrinals,</hi> and in all the <hi>Subſtantials</hi> of true Religion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Difference</hi> then is about leſſer matters, and the Caſe is this;</p>
               <p>The Diſſenters are fully convinced in their Conſciences from the ſtrongeſt and moſt powerful arguments, <hi>That the Word of God contain'd in Scripture, is the onely rule of the whole,</hi> and of <hi>every part of true Religion.</hi> And that what is not according to this Rule is no part, of Proteſtant, or of the true Chriſtian Religion. This great Principle occaſions a twofold Controverſie, the one with the <hi>Papiſt</hi> onely, the other with the <hi>Church of England</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p n="1">1. With the <hi>Papiſt;</hi> for by this <hi>Principle,</hi> we are engag'd to reject whatever Doctrines they impoſe, that are not agreeable to this Rule, and conſequently we reject their Doctrines about <hi>Purgatory, Invocation of Saints, Indulgencies,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe they cannot be found in Scripture. Although there is no Text <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly</hi> forbidding theſe things, yet ſince they are not to be found there, either <hi>directly,</hi> or by <hi>conſequence,</hi> we muſt lay 'em aſide. The Papiſts, 'tis true, make a great busſle, ſaying, where is it aſſerted in Scripture, <hi>no Purgatory,</hi> &amp;c. We reply, where is the <hi>affirmative</hi> to be found. They ſay, that our Religion, as diſtinct from Theirs, is compos'd of <hi>Negatives</hi> onely, which have no foundation in Scripture; We rejoyn by denying their Aſſertion, concluding, That the <hi>Scripture is a ſufficient Rule for our Direction concerning all Religion;</hi> and what is not found there, is not to be embrac'd as a <hi>part</hi> of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. With the <hi>Church of England;</hi> Though we have not this Controverſie as to <hi>Doctrinals,</hi> yet about <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Church-Government</hi> we have The Diſſenters being fully perſwaded, that ſo far as any <hi>Doctrine</hi> about <hi>Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>Church-Government,</hi> is made a part of our Religion, it muſt be brought to the <hi>Rule</hi> of the Scripture; whence if not according to it, though not expreſly forbidden, yet 'tis to be exploded. As for Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49455:17"/>of Worſhip, as Time and Place, <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> &amp;c. they are no part of Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but as touching ſuch Ceremonies, as are made a part of Divine Service, let it be Surplice, ſign of the Croſs, or Salt, and Spittle, or the Chriſme, we reject, as not ſound in Scripture. It being the Principle of Diſſenters to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Scriptures, and to comply with every Scriptural Term of Union, and with no more.</p>
               <p>This being ſo, if any part of their <hi>Service,</hi> that reſpects no <hi>Divine Precept,</hi> be proposd as a <hi>part</hi> of our Religion, yea and as ſuch a <hi>neceſſary</hi> part, as to be the <hi>term of our Communion</hi> with them, we are fully convinc'd, That it is a ſin, and not to be complyed with, unleſs we give up the whole Cauſe to the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>For either the Scriptures are the whole, and onely Rule of the whole, and of every part of our Religion, or not. If <hi>not,</hi> then let us return to <hi>Popery,</hi> or where ſhall we go for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Rule of Religion? But if it be a comple<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Rule, then what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is introduced into our Religion, as a <hi>part</hi> thereof, and not agreeable to the Scriptures, muſt be conſidered, as what ought to be rejected; whence either the <hi>things impoſed</hi> on Diſſenters, and required as <hi>terms</hi> of our Communion with the Church, are a <hi>part of</hi> the Religion of the Church, or <hi>not;</hi> If not, if no part of their Religion, why do they impoſe 'em on us as terms of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, or what, may we be fully of their Religion, and <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent to every part thereof,</hi> and yet be uncapable of their Communion, if ſo, who are the Dividers? I leave it to the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the VViſe. But if it be a <hi>part</hi> of their Religion, 'tis either <hi>agreeable to the Scripture</hi> Rule, or <hi>not;</hi> if <hi>not,</hi> we cannot conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiouſly comply with it, for this is to make <hi>that</hi> a part of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which God hath not: but if according to the Scripture rule, why do they not produce the Scriptural Conſiderations, that are the <hi>Media,</hi> by which they would prove ſo much; or How comes it to paſs, that they are judg d but <hi>Indifferent things,</hi> that are neither commanded, nor forbidden; whereas, whatever is according to the Scripture muſt be according to the revealed VVill of God, for the Scriptures do but contain the <hi>Revealed Will of God,</hi> and therefore, whatever is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scripture, muſt be according to ſome Command in Scripture, ſince a Command is but the Revealed VVill of our
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49455:17"/>great Legiſlator, and if according to ſuch a Command, not <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent;</hi> but if Indifferent not according to the Scripture, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no part of true Religion, and therefore not to be propoſed as a term of Union; or if propoſed as <hi>ſuch,</hi> it cannot without ſin be complyed with.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> then <hi>impoſing</hi> what in their judgment is <hi>but indifferent,</hi> and conſequently what cannot be a part of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, do impoſe as a <hi>term of our Communion</hi> with them, what is in our Conſciences <hi>ſinful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What muſt be done then for Peace and Union, who muſt yield? The <hi>Diſſenters</hi> will part with <hi>every indifferent</hi> thing, rather than break the Peace of the Church; but the <hi>Clergy</hi> hath been hitherto unwilling to part with any <hi>One</hi> Indifferent thing: Yea even now, though the <hi>whole</hi> of Our Religion is in great danger, yet rather than what is <hi>no part</hi> of it ſhould be loſt, let Religion it ſelf Periſh. The Church without ſin can part with their Indifferent Ceremonies, but Diſſenters without ſin cannot comply with them. What then muſt be done for Union? muſt the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> comply in things wherein they <hi>can</hi> without ſin, or muſt Diſſenters ſin, and looſe their peace with God for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion?</hi> The whole of the Controverſie is this, <hi>Whoſe Honour is moſtly to be valued,</hi> that of the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> or that of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> for the Epiſcopal cannot make any <hi>Abatement</hi> of theſe indifferent things conſiſtent with their <hi>Honour;</hi> They have once impos'd theſe things, as terms of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and cannot now <hi>Honourably recede</hi> the leaſt Iota; The <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> they cannot ſtretch their Conſciences to any <hi>ſinful Impoſitions,</hi> but by diſhonouring the Lord Chriſt: What then muſt be done? muſt we to the <hi>diſhonour of</hi> the Lord Chriſt, ſtretch our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and ſin, rather than that the Honour of Epiſcopal Grandeur be fullied by a compaſſionate Condeſcention about Indifferent things, wherein they can without ſin Condeſcend, and which would be really more for their <hi>Juſt Honour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the Caſe; The Diſſenters <hi>would</hi> Unite, but <hi>cannot;</hi> The Epiſcopals <hi>can,</hi> but <hi>will not.</hi> The <hi>Cannot</hi> of Diſſenters, and the Epiſcopals <hi>Will-not</hi> doth make the Diviſion. But who is the <hi>Faulty Divider?</hi> If the true Reaſon of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion lay on the Diſſenters <hi>Will-not,</hi> when they <hi>Can,</hi> 'twould be eaſie to conclude them Obſtinate, and Perverſe; what not to do
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49455:18"/>what they <hi>Can</hi> for Peace? But ſince they <hi>would,</hi> but <hi>cannot</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, how can they be the Dividers.</p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid, 'tis evident, that as 'tis the <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Deſire,</hi> even ſo 'tis the <hi>Principle</hi> of Diſſenters to Unite; Of their ſincerity concerning which, they have ever given Illuſtrious inſtances.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days. In a part of the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> 'tis thus expreſſed of the Diſſenters; <hi>Whoever of them in word or deed gave out any juſt ſuſpition of</hi> Unpeaceable dealing? <hi>Nay have not they ſtriven for peace, in their Miniſterys, in their writings, in their Examples more than any? — But Notwithſtanding this they have been arraigned among</hi> Felons, <hi>and</hi> Theeves; <hi>They have been impriſoned to the uttermoſt, and defaced, and yet they are</hi> ſilent. And Mr. <hi>Dudley Fenner</hi> in his Defence to Dr. <hi>Bridges; anno</hi> 1587. ſaith, All this <hi>they did</hi> patiently bear, <hi>and came daily to the Prayers, to the Baptiſms, and to the Sacraments, and by their Examples and Admonitions kept many from Abuſes, whereto raſhneſs of Zeal would have carried them, yet</hi> now for their labour to their great grief, <hi>they are</hi> openly ſlandered, &amp;c. <hi>Yea, upon every irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious mans complaint in ſuch things as many times are incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to be by the Purſuivants ſent for, to pay two pence for every Mile,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>even when their Families were impoveriſh'd.</hi> But as hath been already hinted, the Providence of God gave them fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in her Majeſties Council, who were convinced of their <hi>peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> diſpoſition, and the regard they had to a walking in all good Conſcience before the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> at this <hi>time</hi> are fully ſenſible, that they are engaged both by <hi>Principle,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> againſt the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and conſequently to <hi>embrace any juſt propoſals for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> will appear from what is declared by divers of them in the account, they give of the Grounds, and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, on which they deſire their Liberty; where 'tis expreſs, <hi>That unto the Reſolution of a ſtedfaſt adherance unto the Proteſtant Religion in Oppoſition unto Popery, we have</hi> (ſay they) <hi>many peculiar engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> For</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <q>Our <hi>Principles</hi> concerning Church Order, Rule, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, wherein we differ from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are not capable of a Compliance with, or Reconciliation unto thoſe of the Papacy, but are contradictory unto them, and utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with them. Where there is an Agreement in general
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49455:18"/>Principles, and men differ onely in their Application unto ſome Particulars, thoſe Differences are capable of a Reconciliation; But where the Principles themſelves are directly contradictory, as it is between us and the Papiſts in this matter, they are capable of no Reconciliation.</q>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <q>We have no <hi>Intereſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> that may be practiſed on, by the Arts, or Inſinuations of the Papiſts. For we are neither capable of any advantages by Eccleſiaſtical Domination, Power, Promotions, with Dignities and Revenues belonging thereunto; which are the principal allurements of the Papacy; nor are engaged in any ſuch Combination Political, or Eccleſiaſtical, as that the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of a few, ſhould draw on the Compliance of the VVhole Party; Theſe things being ut<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erly contrary unto, and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with our Principles, the Papiſts have no way of attempting us, but by meer Force and Violence.</q>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <q>Our fixed Judgment being the ſame with that of all the firſt Reformers; namely, that in the Idolatrous Apoſtacy of the Papal Church, with bloody Perſecutions, the Antichriſtian State foretold in the Scripture doth conſiſt, VVe are for ever exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all thoughts of Compliance with them, or Reconciliation unto them.</q>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <q>VVhereas our Principles concerning Church Order, Rule and VVorſhip, are directly ſuited unto the Diſſolution and Ruine of the Papal Church-State, whence the Papiſts take their VVarranty for all the evil contrivances, which ſome of them are guilty of in this Kingdom, and will ſo far as they are taken out of the Scripture, at length effect it; VVe can have no other expectation from the Prevalency of their Intereſt in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but utter Extirpation, and Deſtruction. VVe are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fully ſatisfied, that our Intereſt and Duty in Self-Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſiſts in a firm Adherence unto the Proteſtant Religion as eſtabliſhed in this Nation, and the Defence thereof, againſt all the attempts of the Papacy.</q>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>So undoubtedly true it is, That the Diſſenters are engaged both by <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Intereſt to oppoſe Popery;</hi> and in order thereunto, muſt (being directed by the Light of Nature) uſe all Proper means for the ſtrengthening themſelves againſt <hi>this</hi> Irreconcileable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49455:19"/>Enemy, the Papiſts; The Union of Proteſtants being the moſt proper Mean, they are Ruin'd if they do not <hi>vnite</hi> when they may. Propoſe any Terms, how difficult ſoever unto Fleſh and Blood, but not <hi>Sinful,</hi> and they'l cloſe with them.</p>
               <p>Thus I have ſhew'n,
<list>
                     <item>1. That the Diſſenters are mov'd by <hi>Interest</hi> to deſire Union.</item>
                     <item>2. That their Principles alſo engage them to do ſo, and conſequently the Dr. is <hi>miſtaken</hi> as to theſe Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I will now proceed to ſhew,</p>
               <p n="3">3. That 'tis the Dr. who falls in with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> entertaining the <hi>ſame Principles,</hi> and arguing from the <hi>ſame Topicks</hi> with him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Bellarm. de notis Eccl. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>— Certum eſt, <hi>concordiam</hi> eſſe ſignum Regni dei, quod ſtare debet in aternum; Diſcordiam autem, Regni Diaboli, quod tandem ruere debet.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth in the general highly extol Union, Peace and Concord in the Church, making it a note of the true Church, even ſo the Dr. (though he doth not make peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord a note of the Church, yet he) doth ſpeak enough of its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and deſireableneſs; For <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is a lovely <hi>Name,</hi> which is in great eſteem even among ſuch, as will not part with a <hi>Toy,</hi> a <hi>Triſte</hi> for the obtaining the <hi>Thing.</hi> But</p>
               <p n="2">2. Notwithſtanding the great commendations given this Union, 'tis not eaſily obtain'd, for moſt frequently the <hi>anteceding Diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are between thoſe different Parties, that are unequally intereſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Favour of the State in which they are; whence things <hi>uſually come</hi> to this iſſue, Thoſe that are uppermoſt, <hi>impoſe</hi> many <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertain,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary</hi> things, as <hi>terms</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> on their Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, with which the more weak and inferiour Party cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly comply. The <hi>Impoſer</hi> is deeply affected with the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous conſequences of the leaſt condeſcention; The <hi>Non-compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> is moſtly employed in minding the Unhappy tendencies of ſevere Impoſitions. The <hi>One</hi> declaims againſt the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> the <hi>Other</hi> againſt the <hi>Miſchief of Impoſitions.</hi> And <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> have had the advantage of the Pleaſure of Impoſing; they <hi>Agree</hi> in theſe particulars.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49455:19"/>
               <p n="1">1. Dr. <hi>Stil.</hi> ſuggeſts the <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> of a <hi>limited Toleration,</hi> and therefore in his diſcourſes about it, his oppoſition is made againſt a General, or an Univerſal, and Unlimited Toleration, even ſo<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Bel.</hi> De Laicis. lib. <hi>3. c. 18.</hi> Sunt qui docent Reges de Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione non debere curare, ſed permittere ſingulis, ut ſentiant prout vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerint, modo non perturbent pacem publicam.—At hic eror Perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioſſimus eſt, &amp; ſine dubio tenentur Principes Chriſtiani— dare ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, ut ea ſides ſervetur quam Epiſcopi Catholoci —docent eſſe tenendam.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> 
                  <q>(There are ſaith he,) ſome, who aſſert, that the Magiſtrate may permit all to <hi>think</hi> what they liſt concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and <hi>live</hi> as they pleaſe, ſuppoſing they break not the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick peace of the State;</hi> but this is a moſt pernicious Errour. Without all doubt, Chriſtian Princes are oblig'd to endeavour to keep their Subjects to the ſame <hi>Faith,</hi> the Catholick Biſhops teach them [yea as to every Punctilio.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As to what the Dr. aſſerts about the <hi>Danger</hi> of receeding from the <hi>ſetled Conſtitution,</hi> as if Toleration would break all in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and not anſwer the end, namely <hi>Peace,</hi> even ſo<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Bell.</hi> ubi ſup. Libertas credendi pernicioſa eſt, etiam temporali bono regnornm, et <hi>publicae paci,</hi> ut patet primum Gregorio lib. <hi>4.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>32.</hi> Et cap. <hi>19.</hi> Sancti patres docuerunt, ut non ſolum fidei ſymbolum ſed etiam ominia al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a Dogmata fidei, licet <hi>Minuta</hi> videan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, inviolata ſervemus, nee propter haereticos ullo modo <hi>immutari</hi> patia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.—Catholici noluerunt, &amp; Imperatori ſcripſerunt, nefarium eſſe de <hi>rebus jam definitis,</hi> aliquid immutari: Et ſi quid juſtarum ſanctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num fuerint immutatum, non propterea <hi>pacem</hi> futuram.—Eſſe p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe. <hi>This and much more againſt the leaſt Relaxation.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who ſaith, <q>'That the <hi>Holy Fathers</hi> obliege us to keep inviolable, not only the Apoſtles Creed, but alſo every other <hi>Opinion of Faith,</hi> though it may ſeem <hi>very minute,</hi> and <hi>inconſiderable;</hi> neither muſt we for the ſake of Hereticks [or <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi>] in any manner ſuffer an Alteration. — The <hi>Catholicks</hi> would not, but wrote to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> that 'twas very wicked to <hi>alter</hi> any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what was formerly <hi>determined,</hi> for if there ſhould be an alteration of <hi>Paenal Laws, Peace</hi> would not enſue, even as the Dr. Tis impoſſible to <hi>ſatisfie all Diſſenters,</hi> and <hi>uncertain</hi> whether any conſiderable number may be gained by a Relaxation.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49455:20"/>
               <p n="3">3. <q>Twill be difficult ſaith the Doctor, on a <hi>Toleration,</hi> to keep Factions out of the Church, for upon the <hi>Principles</hi> laid down by ſome of our <hi>Deſſuting Brethren,</hi> let the Conſtitution be made ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo eaſie to themſelves, yet others may make uſe of their ground, and carry on the differences as high as ever; Even ſo<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Bellar.</hi> ubi ſupra—Non poteſt liberum eſſe in uno quolibet dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, quin eadem ratione liberum eſſe debeat in omnibus, etiam in iis, quae in Symbolo Apoſtolico continentur.—Si ergo credo Eccleſiae tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denti mihi Symbolum Apoſtolorum, quod non ſcio aliunde eſſe Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, niſi quia Eccleſia dicit. Eadem ratione, credere debeo <hi>Sanctos invocandos,</hi> quia eadem Eccleſia hoc dicit, vel ſi hoc poſſim non crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, <hi>eadem ratione</hi> poſſim non credere ſymbolum illud eſſe Apoſtolorum. <hi>Thus the Dr. and</hi> Bellarmine <hi>are agreed, only</hi> Bellarmine <hi>hath the advantage of a Popiſh Principle to countenance his opinion, which will afford the Dr. very little relief, unleſs he will own it, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige 0103 0 us all to</hi> believe, as the Church believes, <hi>from which if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in one thing, we may for the ſame reaſon receede in every thing, becauſe the Church enjoynes a</hi> Ceremony <hi>with the ſame ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it doth the</hi> Apoſtles Creed.</note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who ſaith, 'That Liberty concerning one <hi>Opinion</hi> cannot be allowed, but for the ſame Reaſon it muſt be ſo in every thing, yea, even as to thoſe Doctrines which are contained in the Apoſtles Creed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But as in this, the Dr. and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> agree, even ſo the <hi>Dr.</hi> and the <hi>Church of England differ,</hi> as appears by what is moſt expreſs in Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> who ſaith, <q>I have learnt from the ancient Fathers of the Church, that <hi>nothing is more againſt Religion than to force Religion,</hi> and of St <hi>Paul, the Weapons of the Chriſtian war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare are not carnal.</hi> And great Reaſon; For humane violence may make men <hi>counterfeit,</hi> but cannot make them believe, and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fit for nothing but to breed <hi>form</hi> without, and <hi>Atheiſm</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Beſides if this means of bringing men to embrace any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were generally uſed (as if it may be juſtly uſed in any place by thoſe that have <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>think they have Truth,</hi> certainly they cannot with Reaſon <hi>deny,</hi> but that it may be <hi>uſed</hi> in <hi>every place,</hi> by thoſe that have <hi>power</hi> as well as they, and <hi>think</hi> they <hi>have truth</hi> as well as they) what could follow, but the maintenance of truth, but <hi>perhaps only of the profeſſion of it</hi> in one place, and the <hi>oppreſſion of it in a hundred?</hi> What will follow from it but the preſervation <hi>peradventure</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> but <hi>peradventure</hi> only of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49455:20"/>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in particular States and Churches; but the <hi>immortalizing the greater, and more lamentable diviſions of Chriſtendom</hi> and the World? And therefore what can <hi>follow from it,</hi> but perhaps in the judgment of carnal policy, the <hi>temporal</hi> benefit, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of temporal States and Kingdoms, but <hi>the infinite preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice if not the deſolation of the Kingdom of Chriſt?</hi> And therefore it well becomes them who have their <hi>portions in this Life,</hi> who ſerve no higher State, than that of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> nor this neither any further then that they may <hi>ſerve themſelves</hi> by it, who think of no other happineſs, but the preſervation of their own fortunes, and tranquility in the World; who think of no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means to preſerve States, but humane power, ond <hi>Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villian policie,</hi> and believe no other <hi>Creed</hi> but this, <hi>Regi aut ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitati Imperium habenti nihil injuſtum, quod utile!</hi> Such men as theſe it may become to maintain by <hi>worldly power</hi> and <hi>violence</hi> their <hi>State Inſtrument,</hi> Religion For if all be vain and falſe, (as in their judgment it is) the preſent whatſoever, is better then any, becauſe it is already ſetled; And <hi>alteration of it</hi> may draw with it <hi>change of States,</hi> and the change of State, the <hi>Subverſion of their fortune.</hi> But they that are indeed Servants and Lovers of Chriſt, of Truth, of the Church, and of Mankind, ought with all cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to oppoſe themſelves againſt it, as a common Enemy of all theſe. They that know there is a <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> by whoſe Will and Pleaſure Kings and Kingdoms ſtand and fall, they know, that to no King, or State, any thing can be profitable, which is <hi>unjuſt;</hi> and that nothing can be more evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>unjuſt,</hi> than to <hi>force weak men</hi> by the <hi>profeſſion</hi> of a <hi>Religion,</hi> which they <hi>believe not,</hi> to looſe their own eternal happineſs, out of a vain and needleſs fear, leaſt they may poſſibly diſturb their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral quietneſs. There being no danger to any State from any mans Opinion, unleſs it be ſuch an Opinion by which diſobedience to authority, or impiety is taught or licenced, which ſort I confeſs may juſtly be puniſhed, as well as other faults; or unleſs this ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Doctrine be joyn'd with it, that it is lawful for him by <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane violence</hi> to enforce <hi>others</hi> to it. Therefore if <hi>Proteſtants</hi> did offer <hi>violence to other mens Conſciences,</hi> and <hi>compel them</hi> to embrace their <hi>Reformation,</hi> I excuſe them not.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Although the Dr. ſpeaks ſo much in favour of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> aiming at it, (as it is ſaid) both in his Sermon, and his late great book, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Diviſions as what chiefly gratifies the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49455:21"/>reaſon none can hinder Union, or contribute any thing towards the Continuation of our Diviſions, unleſs they will ſtrengthen the Papal Intereſt, yet the Dr. doth his utmoſt to prevent a Proteſtant Union, and conſequently to maintain Diviſions to the a vancing the Papacy among us.</p>
               <p>That I abuſe not the Dr. will ſoone appear with much Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any that ſhall but conſider.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Dr. is fully apprehenſive from Twenty years ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, That the term of our Union muſt be made more eaſie, or 'tis impoſſible that the Diſſenters ſhould conform, which terms cannot be made more eaſie, unleſs there be an <hi>alterat on</hi> of ſome <hi>Paenal Laws,</hi> againſt which the Doctor doth expreſs himſelf with very much warmth.<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Preface</hi> p. 85.</note> 
                  <q>That <hi>a general unlimited Toleration</hi> to diſſenting Proteſtants will ſoon bring <hi>Confuſion</hi> among us, and in the end <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>opery.</hi>— And a <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> of all <hi>Paenal Laws</hi> that relate to <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> is the ſame thing with a <hi>boundleſs T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ation.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I am heartily ſorry to find the Dr. under this tranſport, and wiſh he would give himſelf the Liberty of <hi>thinking,</hi> though but for a few honrs, for then ſurely he could not but find himſelf oblig'd, when more <hi>cool,</hi> to correct what was the product of an indecent heat, and conſequently diſtinguiſh between a <hi>boundleſs Toleration,</hi> and the ſuſpending each Panal Laws as relate to <hi>Diſſenters only.</hi> Doth not the Dr. know, that the Paenal Laws againſt Diſſenters are only ſuch as engage us to a ſtrict conformity to <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the Worſhipping of God in <hi>Seperate Meetings:</hi> The Paenal Laws that relate to Sabbath breaking, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Felony, Murder, Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> affect the Diſſenters no otherwiſe than the <hi>Conforming Clergy,</hi> for which reaſon, ſeeing a <hi>Boundleſs To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration</hi> is an indulging Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Lying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Dr. muſt mean, That the not conforming to Epiſcopacy and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and the Worſhipping God in Seperate Meetings is the ſame with Drunkenneſs, Uncleanneſs, Perjury, Adultery and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which if true, the off-ſpring of a <hi>Toleration</hi> would be as the Dr. ſaith, <hi>Confuſion.</hi> And is this the Dr's meaning; hath he ſuch high Thoughts of the Divinity of an Humane Ceremony, that what man ſoever neglects it, is as a Murderer, or ſuch low thoughts of worſhipping God in a ſeparate Meeting, that 'tis as Felony? Is not this the equalizing Humane Inventions with Chriſts Inſtitutions?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49455:21"/>Or rather is it not to repreſent the Diſſenters as Perſons that are as vile as the worſt of men, and that it as much concerns the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to puniſh a Diſſenter as a Drunkard and a Felon. This ſhews the Reaſon why Diſſenters are puniſhed as much as Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and therefore unleſs the Parliament incline to favour Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, let them not entertain the Thoughts of giving the Diſſenters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Liberty. But what is this but to cloſe with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>for the ſame reaſon, Liberty is given in the ſame point,</hi> it <hi>may as well</hi> be ſo, in the <hi>greateſt Article of the Creed, i. e.</hi> But the Dr. muſt pardon us, if we are ſo charitable as to believe that whatever ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents ſome of the Inferiour Clergy may entertain concerning Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, or the Dr. himſelf in the midſt of his diſturb'd thoughts, yet theſe are not the apprehenſions of the grave and Judicious Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>England,</hi> nor of the Dr. when free from theſe intemperate heats. They all ſee a difference between a <hi>Conſcientions Diſſenter,</hi> and a profane Debauchee, and that the <hi>former</hi> may be tolerated, when the latter is for his wickedneſs ſeverely puniſhed. However this is enough to prove that the Dr. is againſt the ſhewing any compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to a tender Conſcience, though for the ſake of Union.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Dr. doth ſet a greater value on the <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of men, than on Union, or the relieving tender Conſciences in order unto Union. <q>If (ſaith the Doctor, <hi>page</hi> 89.) any expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent can be found out for the eaſe of other mens Conſciences, without <hi>Reflecting</hi> on our own, if they can be taken in without <hi>Reproach,</hi> or <hi>Diſhonour</hi> to the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the Church; I hope no true Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> will oppoſe it.</q> Theſe are the Dr's. <hi>Terms;</hi> for the underſtanding which, it muſt be obſerv'd that the Diſſenters Not-conforming to Epiſcopacy and the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies is a judging them <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> which is a caſting a Reproach and a diſhonour on the Reformation of the Church, for this ſuppoſeth, that the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is not ſo agreeable to the Scripture as it ought to be. VVhence unleſs Diſſenters can obtain their Liberty in a way conſiſtent with the Honour of their Clergy, it is not to be allowed them, that is, Unleſs they can wound their Conſciences, and fully conform, no Union. All which doth plainly intimate, that an higher eſteem is to be had for the external worldly Honour of men, than for tender Conſciences. But is this the way to heal our Breaches?</p>
               <p>There are ſeveral other inſtances that may be inſiſted on to ſhew the Dr's diſlike of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> as well as of the relieving tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49455:22"/>which are cloath'd with ſo many an uncomely reflection, that 'twill be difficult to diſcover juſt reſentments of them, without falling under the Dr's Cenſure of being <hi>Intemperate,</hi> &amp;c. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will wave them, knowing that there are ſome others more <hi>Able,</hi> and more <hi>Concern'd</hi> to conſider them. So much as to the Dr's many Miſtakes about this Fourth Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>Argument the 5th.</head>
               <p n="5">5. The Diſſenters accepted of His Majeſties Gracious Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, given them Seven or Eight years ago.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Tis the Advice of the Jeſuit <hi>Contzens</hi> (faith the Dr.) in his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the reducing Popery into a Countrey, that it be done under a pretence of <hi>eaſe to tender Conſciences.</hi> The like in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Seignior Bellarini,</hi> that there be an <hi>Indulgence</hi> promoted by the Factious, and ſeconded by the Papiſts. Yea, and <hi>Coleman</hi> owned at his Tryal, and after ſentence declared, That poſſibly he might be of Opinion that Popery might come in, if Liberty of Conſcience had been granted, and 'tis acknowledged, that the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Indulgence,</hi> 167<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was of the Papiſts procuring. But notwithſtanding this by one of the more moderate party of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters wrote, <hi>A publick vindication of their accepting</hi> the <hi>Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and in the year 1675. There was a book printed, entituled <hi>The Peaceable deſign,</hi> or an <hi>account of the Non-conformiſts Meetings,</hi> by ſome Miniſters of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </q> In an Objection it is thus put. <hi>But what ſhall we ſay</hi> then to the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> The Anſwer is, <hi>The Papiſt in our account is</hi> but one ſort of Recuſant, and the <hi>Conſcientious and Peaceable among them,</hi> muſt be held in the ſame Praedicament with thoſe among our ſelves, that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ikewiſe Refuſe to come to Common Prayer. To which the Dr. adds, what is this but joyning for a Toleration of Popery.</p>
               <p>To all which I ſhall ſpeak diſtinctly, and in doing ſo, conſider theſe ſeveral particulars Couched in this Fifth Argument.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That 'tis the Opinion of the Papiſts, that a Toleration might advance their Intereſt:</item>
                  <item>2. That when a Toleration was given through the Papiſts Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, the Diſſenters embraced it.</item>
                  <item>3. That the Diſſenters concurr'd with the Papiſts in the attempts made for a general Toleration.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49455:22"/>
               <p n="1">1. To the Firſt, That the Papiſts apprehended a Toleration ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to their Intereſt.</p>
               <p>Here it muſt be duly obſerv'd, that there is a difference between a Toleration, and a Toleration, <hi>viz.</hi> between a Limited and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited Toleration.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The manner in which a Toleration may be given unto Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Subjects, may be different.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That a Toleration limited to ſuch Diſſenting Proteſtants as are ſound in the Faith, and Peaceable, ſhould advance the Papal Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, is not eaſie to comprehend, nor is it ſaid that the Papiſts apprehend ſo much. Probably the <hi>Jeſuits Contzens, Seignior Bellari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> and <hi>Coleman</hi> might think, that a general Toleration to them, as well as to the Diſſenting Proteſtants might advance their intereſt, but that a Toleration to Proteſtants <hi>only</hi> ſhould contribute any thing towards the reducing this Land to Popery is unimaginable.</p>
               <p>'Tis a known Maxime in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that <hi>Ignorance is the Mother of Devotion,</hi> which is true only with reference to the <hi>Papal Superſtitions.</hi> Let the light of the Goſpel be remov'd, and Popiſh Darkneſs will ſoon ſpred it ſelf over the Face of that Land; but as long as the knowledge of the Goſpel remains, 'tis not eaſie to introduce Popery.</p>
               <p>For which Reaſon a Toleration to Diſſenting Proteſtant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters is ſo far from advancing, that it deſtroys the Papiſts Intereſt. And this is no more then what the <hi>Indulgence granted ſo graciouſly by His Majeſty</hi> did effect, it giving as great a <hi>blow</hi> to Popery, as hath been given it in divers years before. For multitudes who former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly living moſt lewdly, were prepar'd for Popery, being ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of the Truth and excellency of Religious converſation, are moſt firmly engag'd to venture their Lives, yea, their All in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Proteſtant Religion. What then ſhould tempt the Papiſts to conclude a <hi>limited Toleration</hi> to be an Engine prepared for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing a Jeſuitical deſign is to me unknown, unleſs they had a reſpect rather to the <hi>manner of its grant,</hi> than unto the <hi>Toleration it ſelf,</hi> fancying that as his <hi>Preſent Majeſty</hi> indulg'd Proteſtant Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without his Parliament, according to the ſame Rule the <hi>Popiſh S<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſor</hi> they had within their ken, might without his Parliament in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge the Papiſt. But this is only a conjecture of which our <hi>States-Men</hi> are moſt competent Judges, and which whether right or wrong 'tis not to be inſiſted on by the <hi>Clergy</hi> of either way, they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>amcet</hi> to treat of <hi>State-affairs,</hi> which never ſucceeds bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49455:23"/>than when under the <hi>management</hi> and Conduct of States-men, nor never attended with more unhappy <hi>Iſſues,</hi> then when the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy like <hi>buſie bodies</hi> will <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e. Inſpect the Dioceſs of the Laity,</hi> and concern themſelves about what they underſtand not. But what though we grant, that the Papiſts thought a Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence would advance their Intereſt, ſeeing their <hi>thoughts</hi> have no more of Infalibility in them than their <hi>Doctrines,</hi> why doth the Dr. inſiſt on their fancies? What were they never miſtaken? But the Dr. ſuggeſts that <hi>Jeſuits</hi> might creep in under the Notion of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; And can they not rather ſlide into <hi>great preferments</hi> under the Covert of a Gown, a Caſſock, a Surplice? The Temptation ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is greater, and the way much more eaſie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Diſſenters</hi> 'tis ſaid accepted of this Toleration, yea, and wrote a <hi>Publick vindication</hi> of their accepting of it. What then? are they therefore <hi>Popiſhly affected?</hi> What, is <hi>Gratitude</hi> to our Prince confin'd to Papiſts, or their Inſtruments? I cannot but wonder at the diſcourſes of ſome of our Clergy, who delight in nothing ſo much as in railing on the Diſſenters, as <hi>Seditious, Rebellious,</hi> and what not, and yet moſt <hi>angry</hi> with Diſſenters, becauſe they are not <hi>ſo,</hi> as appears by the many <hi>Invectives,</hi> that were written againſt our <hi>thankful acknowledgments</hi> of His Majeſties <hi>Clemency.</hi> But though this Dr. and ſome others are angry, yet 'tis the Reſolve of Proteſtant Diſſenters to be ready on all occaſions to ſhew their Loyalty and thankfulneſs to his Majeſty for every inſtance of his Bounty towards his diſſenting, but moſt dutifull and loving Subjects.</p>
               <p>But wherein is the Papiſt gratified by that Toleration, what did he gain by it? Did he enjoy <hi>more liberty</hi> after, than before? Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, the import of the great cry of our Clergy is this, That the Diſſenters muſt not be permitted to enjoy, as <hi>much</hi> as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and be on <hi>even terms</hi> with them, to the advancing the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion. For this is evident, that when there was no <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> for Indulging Proteſtants, there was no <hi>proſecution of Paenal Laws</hi> on Papiſts; yea, when the <hi>Clergy</hi> were moſt ſevere in proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Proteſtants; the Papiſts knew not practically what a <hi>Paenal Statute</hi> meant, and yet our Church men very ſilent. But his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty according to the Gracious Propenſions of his heart no ſooner ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his Clemency towards the <hi>Poor Diſſenting Proteſtants,</hi> but the cry is <hi>Popery, Popery,</hi> that is, poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in a Bears, the Papiſts skin, are envied and malign'd.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49455:23"/>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Diſſenters wrote favourably of the</hi> Tolerating Papiſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Before the Diſcovery of the Plot, the Papiſts were judg'd <hi>Loyal Subjects,</hi> though <hi>Saperſtitious,</hi> &amp;c. even by our <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> and <hi>Clergy.</hi> Doth not Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> remember, that a R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Divine, a Son of the Church, no way inferiour to himſelf, did write <hi>ex induſtria</hi> in favour of the <hi>Loyal Papiſt?</hi> Is the Church of <hi>England</hi> therefore for Popery? How then can Diſſenters he ſo, ſeeing the reaſon for the one and the other is the ſame, with this difference, namely, The Diſſenter gave but an <hi>hint,</hi> which did rather diſcover a <hi>confidence</hi> in, and <hi>humble de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ercing</hi> to the <hi>Wiſdom of our Magiſtracy;</hi> who did not judge meet at that time to be brisk in a proſecuting the Paenal Laws againſt them for their <hi>Recuſancy:</hi> but the Plea of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> in favour of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick was more than an <hi>hint,</hi> it was a <hi>conſiderable Treatiſe.</hi> But</p>
               <p n="2">2. Since the Diſcovery of the Plot the Papiſts are better known, they are <hi>now</hi> known to be <hi>Implacable Enemies</hi> to a Proteſtant Prince and Kingdom; to be <hi>Turbulent,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npeaceable:</hi> Whence the Tolerating them, and the Kingdoms peace are become inconſiſtent, and as the one is advanc'd, the other neceſſarily muſt be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown: For which Reaſon, our Superiours, Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, do ſee cauſe to paſs <hi>another</hi> Judgment on the Papiſts than formerly they did, whereby the <hi>Diſſenter</hi> may with the greater freedom appear againſt them, giving our Soveraign, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament the fulleſt aſſurances of <hi>Loyalty</hi> to His Majeſty, and <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> to the Proteſtant Religion, being ready to <hi>hazard their lives</hi> and their <hi>all,</hi> in the defence of <hi>them</hi> and <hi>it.</hi> How then can they be ſuppos'd Favourers of Popery, or rather how can Dr. <hi>Stil.</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe after this manner? For, if ſuch as are under the laſh of Paenal Laws for Conſcience ſake, muſt be thought to be <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> for not animating the Magiſtrate to a Proſecution of Paenal Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt other <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> Conſcientious, and Peaceable Diſſenters as the Papiſts were <hi>then judg'd</hi> to be, by many of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and this before the Diſcovery of their Horrid Plots, I ſay, if the whole Party of Diſſenters muſt be thus expos'd, ſo ſeverely for ſuch an hint as that was, what ſhall we think of Dr. <hi>S.,</hi> who ſpeaks ſo <hi>favourably of the Papiſts,</hi> ſuggeſting <hi>even now,</hi> that when Mens heats againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which are ſaid to be beyond the juſt bounds of <hi>Prudence, Decency,</hi> and <hi>Humanity;</hi> are over, it will be thought great <hi>hardſhip</hi> for the Papiſts <hi>onely,</hi> to be deprived of the Liberty of their Conſciences, when the <hi>wildeſt of the Fanaticks</hi> are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49455:24"/>allowed it. <hi>What,</hi> may the Dr. inſinuate ſo much in their Favour <hi>now,</hi> and not expoſe himſelf to the Cenſure; and muſt a Diſſenter who ſpake not half as much in other times, be ſo ſeverely treated? But whether the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are favourers of the Papal Faction, will more fully appear by the Anſwer that ſhall be given unto his 6th. Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> 6.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Diſſenters, ſince the Diſcovery of the late Horrid Plot</hi> did <hi>cloſe with the People</hi> in an over-fierce oppoſing the Papiſts. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith the Dr.) <hi>now the Diſſenters tack about, and ſtrike in with the</hi> Rage of the People, <hi>and none ſo fierce againſt Popery as they, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they</hi> mar <hi>a good buſineſs by</hi> over-doing <hi>it.</hi> Praef. pag. 34.</p>
               <p>This is ſuggeſted more than once, but becauſe of the <hi>ſtrangeneſs</hi> of the <hi>medium</hi> at this juncture, and its unmeetneſs for its deſigned end, I'l not be over-curious in conſidering it; It being well known that <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plots are laid ſo deep, the Plotter ſo cruel, yea, and ſo reſolv'd for Proteſtant Blood, the Blood of our Prince, our Nobles, our Gentry, our Miniſtry, and People, that unleſs we by a ſerious and humble Repentance return to God, putting our Truſt in the Lord, and aſſume an undaunted Courage, we are a loſt People. To be at ſuch a time <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>indifferent,</hi> is to relinquiſh and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our Religion. For if there be any Fire of Zeal againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the houſe, it cannot but flame out at the Windows at this time; for the ſtormy winds of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Cruelties and Treaſons, deſolating Threatnings, and implacable Fury, are ſuch as muſt cauſe the leaſt ſpark of Zeal for <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c. to break out into a flame, that cannot be hid; Which may be, even when our Zeal doth not tranſport us to any <hi>Irregular</hi> or <hi>Illegal</hi> proceedings, which can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerve the Epithets of <hi>Indecent</hi> and <hi>Inhumane;</hi> with which Proteſtant Diſſenters cannot juſtly be charg'd, and therefore the <hi>Surprize</hi> is the greater to find ſuch an Intimation in ſo Judicious, and Wiſe a Perſon as Dr. <hi>S.</hi> In what reſpect doth, or can the Dr. accuſe them? Are the Diſſenters too Zealous in <hi>Declaiming</hi> againſt Popiſh <hi>Principles,</hi> and <hi>Practiſes?</hi> Do they repreſent <hi>Papal Treaſons</hi> to be more <hi>hainous than they are</hi> (i. e.) more bloody, or more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane and Cruel? What acts of Inhumanity have they exerciſed? or in what reſpects have they been tranſported beyond the juſt bounds of Prudence, Decency, or Humanity? Why is not the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49455:24"/>Dr. more particular in his Charge, ſeeing <hi>Dolus latet in Generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus?</hi> 'Tis their <hi>Joyning with the People</hi> (the Dr. adds) but in what? In <hi>Petitioning his Majeſty</hi> for the <hi>Sitting of the Parliament,</hi> ſurely the Dr. wo'nt now judge that to be ſeditious? Is it our <hi>Readineſs,</hi> when call'd thereunto to hazard our lives to ſave his Majeſtie's? or what? ſeeing the Dr. doth not faſten any particular crime on the Diſſenters, and the Diſſenters being Innocent, have no guilty Conſcience to accuſe them, nor are they able to divine; It cannot be expected, that we ſhould be more full in the Conſideration of it, neither is there any need, for enough hath been ſaid to clear the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbecoming Reproaches,</hi> the Dr. would faſten on them; Yea, enough hath been hinted to evince the Dr's. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes</hi> to have been <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. I'le now proceed to the third Particular, and give a <hi>Summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Account</hi> of the Unhappy Tendencies of theſe Great and Many Miſtakes, as they are adjuſted for an Advance of the Papal Intereſt.</p>
               <p n="1">§. 1. 'Tis Remarkable, That Notwithſtanding the Honourable Apprehenſions the Dr. may have of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> very little, if any thing, is hinted concerning the <hi>moſt Principal part</hi> thereof, namely, <hi>Proteſtant Doctrines:</hi> The which I do the rather obſerve, becauſe it hath been of late years, the <hi>ſole care</hi> of our Eccleſiaſticks to <hi>ſecure</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Religion,</hi> without uſing any Mean for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Proteſtant <hi>Doctrines;</hi> and accordingly <hi>new Declarations, Subſcriptions</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> have been offered for the more firm eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> even when our Doctrines have been ſadly vitiated by ſome of the <hi>Sons of the Church,</hi> without any other notice, than the <hi>Complaints</hi> of a <hi>Few,</hi> ſuch as are Dr. <hi>Tully,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. That <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are conſidered by the Dr. as the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Reformation,</hi> the <hi>Bulwark</hi> of Proteſtant Religion, even Epiſcopacy and Ceremonies, as <hi>diſſented from</hi> by the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> (i. e) That Epiſcopacy, and thoſe Ceremonies unto which the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> cannot conſcientiouſly conform. 'Tis this that cannot be diſſented from without great diſhonour unto Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, viz. The <hi>Reformation;</hi> which, ſtrictly conſidered, is no part of the Reformation, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> as much of theſe things as Diſſenters agree not unto, cannot be juſtly called Reformation.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49455:25"/>For what parts of the Papal Epiſcopacy and Ceremonies are rejected, the Diſſenters heartily in their rejection cloſe with the Epiſcopal; that is, ſo far as there is a <hi>Reformation;</hi> But, as to the Particular wherein the <hi>Difference</hi> lies between the Conformiſt and Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt, there is no <hi>Reformation</hi> on the Conformiſts part. I am not now diſputing againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> or <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> but ſuppoſing them <hi>Apoſtolical;</hi> yet I aſſert, they cannot be conſidered, as a <hi>part of Reformation:</hi> For Reformation doth preſuppoſe ſome <hi>Anteced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Corruption</hi> of the thing to be Reformed; Reformation conſiſting in the removing the Corruptions, and therefore we do not ſay, that the Proteſtants <hi>Reform'd</hi> what was never <hi>Corrupted;</hi> for inſtance, The Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> not being corrupted by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Proteſtants are not ſaid to Reform it, even ſo, That <hi>Part of Epiſcopacy and Ceremonies,</hi> which is conſidered as <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> and hath been, and ſtill is maintain'd by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that part if adhered unto, as Apoſtolical by Proteſtants, is but the <hi>Retaining</hi> an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncorrupted</hi> part of our good old Religion, and not a <hi>Reforming</hi> it, Thus even do the<note n="*" place="bottom">Becan. Opuſc. Tit. <hi>II.</hi> Queſt. <hi>9.</hi> Hanc Hierarchiam ex parte <hi>retinent</hi> Calviniſtae in <hi>Anglia</hi> — extra <hi>Angliam</hi> penitus rejiciunt. Quo nomine male audiunt ab eodem Rege, qui in Monitoriâ praefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ad Imperatorem, Reges &amp; Principes, de hac re ita ſcribit; Quo ſtudio in Epiſcoporum &amp; Eccleſiaſticae Hierarchiae defenſionem ſemper incubui, eodem in confuſam illam Anarchiam, &amp; parilitatem Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum invectus ſum. Et infra, Mihi praecipuus labor fuit, dejectos Epiſtopos reſtituere, &amp; Puritanorum Anarchiam repugnare. Et rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem addit, quia cum in caeteris rebus ordo quidum de diſpoſitio ſit, etiam in Eccleſia eſſe neceſſe eſt.</note> Jeſuits conſider it. But grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the <hi>Retained</hi> part of the Hierarchy, &amp;c. may be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as <hi>Reformed,</hi> it ſtill muſt be aſſerted,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That 'tis <hi>no Part</hi> of the <hi>Lutheran,</hi> and <hi>Tranſmarine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Reformation;</hi> for, they conſider it as what ſtands in need of a <hi>Reformation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Dr. making this the <hi>Great Part</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, doth but exalt a part of the Papal Hierarchy under the name of <hi>Reformation,</hi> for which Reaſon, even other parts of the <hi>ſame,</hi> may deſerve his Applauſes under the ſame Notion, and what is this but to reflect on all Proteſtants beſides themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49455:25"/>
               <p n="3">§. 3. This <hi>Reformation</hi> in Conjunction with the Papiſts, an adhering unto the <hi>Praelacy of Biſhops,</hi> and in <hi>Oppoſition</hi> unto moſt other Proteſtants, an exploding Godly Peoples <hi>Right</hi> of chooſing their own Paſtor. And Thirdly, an introducing ſuch little <hi>Ceremomes</hi> as do but prepare the way for greater.</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. All this is moſt admirably accompliſhed with the Help of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and other <hi>Jeſuites</hi> in that, this Noble Superſtructure is faſtned on the Foundation of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality,</hi> the <hi>ſure</hi> Notes of what is <hi>Apoſtolical;</hi> for, (ſaith the Dr.) if this ſhould be a Corruption how comes it to be ſo <hi>Antiem,</hi> and ſo ſoon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,</hi> even <hi>inſenſibly</hi> without any noiſe.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. This is a <hi>Receeding</hi> from the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and a Rebuilding what the Church hath <hi>demoliſhed,</hi> a ſetting too great an <hi>Honour</hi> on thoſe <hi>Jeſuitical Arguments,</hi> which have been exploded by the Church, as appears out of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as one Apprehenſive of their weakneſs, the Doctor doth proceed.</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. To the old Argument, <hi>vide Miſchievous Impoſitions,</hi> as what cannot but moſt effectually compaſs his end, that is, under the notion of oppoſing a <hi>Toleration,</hi> to introduce a <hi>ſmart Proſecuting</hi> of Paenal Laws againſt ſuch, as cannot receive Convictions from the foregoing Arguments. That the Dr. writes againſt <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as</hi> conſiſts in the ſuſpending thoſe <hi>Paenal Laws,</hi> which are againſt <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> is evident: And what is the meaning of this, if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns not the urging a Proſecution of Paenal Laws? Doth a ſuſpending the Paenal Laws any otherwiſe diſpleaſe him, than as it prevents a <hi>Proſecution</hi> of the Law againſt Diſſenters? And if by theſe Laws Diſſenters muſt be proſecuted, for not aſſenting unto what they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>conſcientiouſly</hi> aſſert. Is not this laying our <hi>Faculties</hi> under <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> or a <hi>Forcing Religion,</hi> an introducing <hi>blind obedience</hi> with a <hi>Whip?</hi> That ſuch Doctrines are pleaſing to the Papiſt, might be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily proved from the advantages they have taken from Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> and ſome others; who have expreſs'd themſelves too liberally in their <hi>Invectives</hi> againſt Diſſenting Proteſtants, and that the Dr hath no way gratified the Epiſcopal <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by <hi>Relinquiſhing</hi> their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is to be ſeen in Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> who hath ſhewn the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious conſequences</hi> of ſuch Impoſitions. Namely,</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49455:26"/>
               <p n="1">1. As it may occaſion an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in ſome particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; even ſo it doth <hi>Immortalize</hi> the greater and more <hi>Lamentable Diviſions of Chriſtendome,</hi> and the World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it may in the judgment of <hi>Carnal Policy</hi> advance the <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral benefit,</hi> and tranquility of Temporal States, and Kingdoms; even ſo 'twill be followed with the <hi>Infinite Prejudice,</hi> if not the <hi>deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Kingdom of Chriſt; and therefore this is a Doctrine that becomes none, but ſuch whoſe <hi>Creed</hi> is <hi>Regi aut Civitati imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um habenti nibil injuſtum,</hi> q<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od <hi>utile,</hi> who dread the change of State, leaſt it ſhould <hi>change their Fortunes.</hi> But</p>
               <p n="3">3 This cannot be profitable unto any King or State, becauſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt,</hi> for nothing is more evidently <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust,</hi> than to <hi>force weak men</hi> by the profeſſion of a Religion, which they <hi>believe</hi> not, to looſe their own Eternal happineſs out of a <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>needleſs fear,</hi> leaſt they may poſſibly diſturb their Temporal quietneſs.</p>
               <p>I hope, ſeeing the Dr. will find theſe Arguments in one of the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> diſcourſes, he will give ſome heed thereunto, and perceive how he hath <hi>unawares</hi> given advantage to the Papiſt.</p>
               <p>Thus the Dr. in his pretences againſt Popery, <hi>falls</hi> into the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for which he reproveth the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> which I have evinced out of his <hi>own Preface,</hi> as compar'd with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> with whom he <hi>accords,</hi> and with the <hi>Old Proteſtants,</hi> from whom in ſome of theſe things at leaſt, he <hi>diſſents,</hi> The which I have done with the <hi>greateſt fairneſs</hi> and <hi>integrity,</hi> without any deſign of forcing his words to ſpeak what is not according to their <hi>Grammatical ſence,</hi> and <hi>common acceptation,</hi> omitting the inſiſting on ſeveral points, that might be ſpoken unto with greater diſadvantage unto the Dr. But aiming principally at the clearing the <hi>Innocent,</hi> who are by him accuſed, and the ſhowing into what <hi>Miſtakes</hi> his tranſport hath carried him, I hinted no more than what was neceſſary in order thereunto, carefu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhunning as much as the <hi>Subject matter</hi> would permit any ſuch expreſſion, as might be judg'd by the Dr's own <hi>intimates</hi> Indecent; humbly apprehending that the Dr's Miſtakes are but evincements of the emotions of that Corruption, which in part is in the beſt of Saints on Earth, which calls rather for our <hi>Compaſſion</hi> than Triumph, knowing that we our ſelves are but men of like paſſions. For which reaſon I will draw to a cloſe in ſpeaking to the Fourth thing.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That to the end the Dr. may <hi>do himſelf,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> but <hi>right,</hi> 'tis neceſſary that <hi>he be either more diſtinct,</hi> and <hi>full</hi> in a <hi>further explication</hi> of his ſentiments, if he be miſapprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49455:26"/>or that he will be ſo <hi>Candid,</hi> as to go <hi>on in following</hi> Bellarmine in one thing more, namely, in that it deſerves due eſteem and regard by a <hi>ſecond Retractation,</hi> if theſe miſtakes appears to be ſuch as they are by me repreſented.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If the Dr. hath not wrong'd the Diſſenter, nor clos'd with the Jeſuit in his arguings againſt Diſſenters, 'tis moſt apparent, that his words need an <hi>Expoſition,</hi> for whatſoever <hi>unprejudiced</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon conſiders, what hath been ſaid in the foregoing Diſcourſe, may eaſily perceive, that if we muſt judge of his meaning by his writing, 'tis as I have ſaid; But, if not <hi>ſo,</hi> I beſeech the Dr. to exerciſe his <hi>Candour</hi> in inlightning us, aſſuring him, as ſoon as <hi>I</hi> can underſtand that <hi>I</hi> have in any reſpect miſrepreſented him, <hi>I</hi> will be ſo <hi>Juſt,</hi> as to acknowledge ſo much, and do my utmoſt for the clearing him, and in order thereunto have this onely to add, That <hi>I do not ſay,</hi> the Doctor hath <hi>conſulted the Jeſuits,</hi> for what he <hi>aſſerts ſo agreeably unto their writings</hi> (God forbid I ſhould aſſert what I do not know) But this I ſay <hi>that</hi> the <hi>Agreement</hi> is as <hi>great</hi> in thoſe inſtances I have mentioned, as if he <hi>had,</hi> and that if he <hi>hath not conſult'd them,</hi> I know not what can be aſſigned as the true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this <hi>ſtrange agreement,</hi> unleſs it be, that ſometime <hi>great Wits</hi> jump, or, that ſuch is the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Controverſie</hi> between <hi>Him,</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> that there is no way ſo effectual for the confuting us, but by proceeding on <hi>Jeſuitical Principles,</hi> and <hi>uſing Popiſh</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But</p>
               <p n="2">2. If I have neither miſtaken, nor miſrepreſented the Dr. as, I verily believe, I have not, ſeeing the Dr. is <hi>fallible,</hi> and may ſee cauſe to alter his Sentiments unto theſe particulars, as well as he hath done with reference unto ſome others, the He would be ſo <hi>Self-denying</hi> on his receiving <hi>Convictions,</hi> as to intimate ſo much unto the <hi>World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Dr. changeth his <hi>judgement</hi> concerning ſome Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons relating to Religion, is neither a <hi>wonder to the World,</hi> nor ſhould it be a Reproach unto him, or any other Perſon, that for ſufficient Reaſons doth ſo. Yet</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whenever any conſiderable <hi>Tract</hi> is with the <hi>ſhew,</hi> and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſtrength</hi> of much Reaſon publiſhed to the World, through the Varniſh of which, in proceſs of time, the <hi>Author</hi> eſpies <hi>Miſtakes</hi> and <hi>Errour,</hi> as the <hi>Author</hi> acts ingenuouſly in Publiſhing ſo much unto the World, even ſo he <hi>ought</hi> to do the World that piece of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> as to be at the pleaſing Trouble of confuting it himſelf,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49455:27"/>ſeeing otherwiſe, much miſchief may be done the poor <hi>weak Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> who thinks the diſcourſe to contain the ſame Reaſons, ſince a a <hi>Retractation,</hi> which it did before, may through the <hi>Influence</hi> of of thoſe Arguments, that are in it, be oblig'd to adhere unto <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</hi> Moreover as to the Dr's. Caſe, 'tis preſum'd he doth not retract the <hi>whole,</hi> and every part of his <hi>Irenicum,</hi> and therefore 'twould be neceſſary ſomewhat be done to ſhew, what needs <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> what a <hi>Retractation,</hi> and for what Reaſons a <hi>Retractation;</hi> and the like as to this <hi>preſent great Book,</hi> a <hi>part</hi> of whoſe <hi>Prefaced</hi> I have Animadverted on, which Animadverſions are of ſuch a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as cannot but engage the Dr. to do ſomewhat of this <hi>kind;</hi> even as<note n="†" place="bottom">Bellarm. Recog. Scripſi, Deo teſte, quod verum eſſe exiſtimavi, non gratiam hominum, vel propriam utilitatem, ſed Honorem Dei, &amp; Eccleſiae Commodum reſpiciens. Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in ſcriptis meis aliquid a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis literis <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aut ſanctorum Patrum Regulis alienum, ſciens, poſui. Quin tamen ſcriptumeſt <hi>Prov. 10.</hi> in multiloquio non deerit Peccatum, quod etiam de multa ſcriptione dei poſſe non dubito S. <hi>Auguſtinum</hi> imitatus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf in a like Caſe hath done, who, in the End of his Diſputations hath his particular <hi>Recognitions,</hi> prefacing it in theſe words, <q>God is my VVitneſs, that what I have written is no more than what I judg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to be the Truth, which I wrote not on any unworthy deſign of pleaſing others, or profiting my ſelf, but with an Aim at Gods Glory, and the Churches Benefit. Nor have I knowingly receeded either from the Rule of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures or Holy Fathers, However, ſince 'tis ſaid, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.19. In the multitude of words there wanteth not ſin, which I Queſtion not but may be ſaid of much writing, I will therefore imitate St. <hi>Auſtin, i. e.</hi> in his Retractations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>That we may exerciſe the Charity in hoping that the Dr. doth not at any time publiſh <hi>That</hi> to be a <hi>Truth</hi> which he believeth to be an <hi>Errour,</hi> and with all finding the Dr. to <hi>miſtake,</hi> yea ſometimes <hi>ſenſible of his Miſtakes.</hi> I have preſum'd to recommend unto him not onely St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> but alſo the great <hi>Bellarmine</hi> as a Pattern for his <hi>Imitation,</hi> it being an <hi>Honour</hi> to follow him in what is <hi>Right,</hi> when no way ſo as to thoſe particulars, wherein he is an Enemy unto the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt and the True Proteſtant <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:49455:27"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
